<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full and satisfactorie ansvver to the late vnaduised bull, thundred by Pope Paul the Fift, against the renowmed state of Venice being modestly entitled by the learned author, Considerations vpon the censure of Pope Paul the Fift, against the common-wealth of Venice: by Father Paul of Venice, a frier of the order of Serui. Translated out of Italian.</title>
            <title>Considerationi sopra le censure della Santità di Papa Paolo V. contra la serenissima republica di Venetia. English</title>
            <author>Sarpi, Paolo, 1552-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full and satisfactorie ansvver to the late vnaduised bull, thundred by Pope Paul the Fift, against the renowmed state of Venice being modestly entitled by the learned author, Considerations vpon the censure of Pope Paul the Fift, against the common-wealth of Venice: by Father Paul of Venice, a frier of the order of Serui. Translated out of Italian.</title>
                  <title>Considerationi sopra le censure della Santità di Papa Paolo V. contra la serenissima republica di Venetia. English</title>
                  <author>Sarpi, Paolo, 1552-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 76, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Sarpi, Paolo.  Considerationi sopra le censure della Santità di Papa Paolo V. contra la serenissima republica di Venetia.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An answer to the late bull of Pope Paul the Fift, against the renowmed state of Venice.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paul --  V, --  Pope, 1552-1621.</term>
               <term>Donato, Leandro, 1536-1612.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Pope (1605-1621 : Paul V). --  1606 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Italy --  Venice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  History --  Papal Interdict, 1606-1607 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17247:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FVLL AND SATISFACTORIE ANSWER TO THE LATE VNADVISED Bull, thundred by Pope <hi>Paul the Fift, againſt the renowmed</hi> State of VENICE: <hi>Being modestly entitled by the learned Author,</hi> CONSIDERATIONS VPON the Cenſure of Pope PAVL the Fift, <hi>against the Common-wealth</hi> of VENICE:</p>
            <p>By Father PAVL of VENICE, a Frier of the Order of <hi>Serui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Italian.</hi> PSAL. 108.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <p>MALEDICENT ILLI, ET TV BENEDICES.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for IOHN BILL. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17247:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17247:2"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS vpon the cenſure of Pope <hi>Paul the Fift,</hi> againſt the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> hath euer conſtantly held, that the principall foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all dominion and empire was layed in true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and pietie; and hereof (by the ſpecial grace of God) it hath had experience, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene begun, inſtituted, and augmented in true diuine worſhip: the which with great care ſhe hath alwayes ſought to encreaſe, eſpecially by building many religious houſes, and magnificently adorning of the ſame, furniſhing them with decent Miniſters, and enterteining of thoſe religious Orders which age after age the Catholike Church hath brought forth. A manifeſt teſtimony whereof appeareth in the great number of Churches richlie endowed, and the largeneſſe of Monaſteries, not only in the citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> but alſo in others ſubiect to the ſame; and that alwayes with a conuenient and neceſſary reſpect to cut off all thoſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which might be hurtfull to her cities and dominions, through ſuch innouations as vſually creepe in vnder the pretext of Colleges, Frieries, Societies, or Conuents, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17247:3"/> to the danger and dammage which great buildings, erected and ſituated in vnfit places, bring vnto a publike ſecuritie: for ſhe had alwayes a ſpeciall conſideration what ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons made entrance into her citie, and in what places Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and Churches had their foundations, the better to nouriſh and enterteine them: and when they but perceiued that common and ordinary diligence was not enough, from the yeere 1337 a Law was enacted, That in <hi>Venice</hi> there ſhould be no Churches, Monaſteries, Hoſpitals, nor other ſuch like places built without licence. The which law was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards renewed and confirmed in 1515 and in 1561: but then perceiuing, that ſuch a like care was alſo neceſſary to be had ouer other land and maritime townes, in the yeere 1603 commandement was giuen to all Rectors and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, that from that time forwards they ſhould not permit any Religious or Lay perſon whatſoeuer to build Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Churches, Hoſpitals, or other Conuents of Religious or Secular, without licence from the Senate, vnder penalties of baniſhment to their perſons, and of confiſcation of the building and ground.</p>
            <p>The Common-wealth alſo was euer of this opinion, that as for the time paſt ſhe had beene exemplarly preſerued, ſo in like maner, that it ought to be cared for hereafter, with the adminiſtration of ſincere and incorrupted iuſtice, execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ouer her ſubiects, knowing what the holy Scripture ſaith: <hi>Regnum de gente in gentem transfertur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 10.</note> 
               <hi>propter iniuſtitias, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurias, contumelias, &amp; diuerſos dolos.</hi> And ſo on the contrary: <hi>Rex qui iudicat in veritate pauperes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29.</note> 
               <hi>thronus eius in aeternum fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabitur.</hi> Wherefore ſhe mainteining euery one in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his goods, together with the ſpeciall protection and defence of euery ones honour, ſhe hath mainteined and happily perpetuated publike tranquillitie and peace; the which, that it might not be diſturbed by vniuſt vſurpations and iniuries towards others, diuers Eccleſiaſticall perſons hauing many times beene conuicted of enormous and hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offences, who rather, by the goodneſſe of their life and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17247:3"/> maners (as their duetie is) ſhould exempt themſelues from criminall iuſtice; the Common-wealth did not forbeare to execute it vpon them, ſo farre as was neceſſarie for publike ſafetie, granting them notwithſtanding an immunitie from the Magiſtrates, in common tranſgreſsions, for a fauour to that Order, after the example of other neighbour-princes; ſhe euer by this meanes keeping the wicked in feare, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying thoſe that were in any wiſe offended: ſo that ſhe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thus the power granted vnto her by God, ſhe hath from her firſt beginning vnto theſe preſent times accuſtomed to ſentence and puniſh, in caſe of grieuous offence, any perſon Eccleſiaſticall, of what degree or Order ſoeuer: and by this meanes ſhe hath gone forward in enioying and practiſing, with publike tranquillitie and peace, the ancient and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent libertie of her true dominion.</p>
            <p>In like maner, the Common-wealth hath laboured at all times to keepe her ſubiects abundant in poſſeſſions and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubſtance, ſhe knowing how principally it did import for publike ſecuritie, if the priuate were well accommodated: whereupon, about ſome three hundred yeeres ſince, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to obſerue, that the Clergy contended daily to augment in poſſeſſions and reuenewes; a matter notwithſtanding (though peraduenture they had no ſuch intention) which fell not out onely to the loſſe and preiudice of ſecular fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, which of neceſſitie muſt needs decay vpon the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their goods; but further, to the detriment of the publike reuenewes and incomes, and alſo of publike force: for when the number of Citizens which were liable, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ciuill gouernments, impaired, and the quantitie of their goods diminiſhed; vpon which the publike reuenew was raiſed; and ſo, on the contrary, the number of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſons augmenting, which pretended exemption from all the neceſſarie offices and functions of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and their goods increaſing; of neceſſitie it muſt needs come to paſſe, that all publike intereſts would be wonderfully impaired.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17247:4"/>
            <p>Vnto this may be added another matter, which is, That the Clergy neuer alienating of any thing, but with their great aduantage and benefit, and the Churches, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall; if they alwayes purchaſed, and the Seculars impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; it muſt neceſſarily in the end come to paſſe, that all the wealth would reſt in the Clergies hands, and all Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and Ciuilitie would haue beene vtterly extinguiſhed, the world being reduced to theſe two ranks of men, Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and Peaſants.</p>
            <p>To preuent therefore ſo grieuous and notable an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, the Common-wealth ordeined, the yeere 1333, that there ſhould not be giuen or bequeathed to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the perpetuitie of any thing ſtable within the Citie and Dukedome of <hi>Venice;</hi> and yet if that any ſuch bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were made, after a certeine time, it ſhould be ſold, and the price thereof to remaine to the Church. The which law was obſerued diuerſly, til the yere 1536, when it was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed after this maner: That none might leaue any thing ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Church for aboue the tearme of two yeres; during which time it was to be ſold; and this not being performed by Eccleſiaſticks themſelues, a Magiſtrate ſhould be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to execute the ſame. And from the foreſayd lawes, at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times, ſo great both publike and priuate good hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, that ſome other ſubiect Cities, euen out of their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipall conſtitutions, decreed the ſame, partly of olde, and partly in theſe our dayes. Which things, when the Senate had well pondered, to reduce their whole State to an vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and to preuent the diminution of ſecular ſubſtance, in the yeere 1605 they promulged a Law which was ordeined for the Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> and together extended it ſelfe to the whole State; adding furthermore, That no man in the Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> or thorow the whole State, might vnder any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour whatſoeuer, ſell, giue, or by any other meanes alienate to an Eccleſiaſticall perſon, any thing ſtable, without licence of the Senate, to be granted them after the ſame maner and forme as was vſually granted in the alienations of goods
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17247:4"/> publike, and that euery alienation otherwiſe performed, ſhould be fruſtrate, and the ſtable confiſcated, with a penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſet vpon the Notaries.</p>
            <p>For which conſiderations, three yeeres before, 1602, to moderate the ſuperabundant purchaſe of the Clergie, who vnder pretext of their direct title in ſome things of theirs poſſeſſed by the Laitie, went about euery day to appropriate the ſame to themſelues, ſuing ſometimes one, and then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the poſſeſſors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Enfiteuſi</hi> new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly planted or engrafted.</note> and impoſing the tearme of <hi>Enfiteuſi</hi> vpon all their Leaſes and Perpetuities; and by this meanes pretending dayly a right in all ſales, that either the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors were decayed,<note place="margin">When direct heire failed, to one but collaterally allied.</note> or that the goods could not deſcend to euery kinde of heire; to the great preiudice of the ſubiects, who were entangled and moleſted in continuall brabbles and ſutes: vpon occaſion of a certeine controuerſie mooued by the Monks of <hi>Pragia,</hi> the Senate decreed, that Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches might not appropriate to themſelues goods poſſeſſed by the Laity, <hi>per praelationem lineae, cum ſolidatione vtilis,</hi> their direct right and freehold ſtill reſerued. The which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, conſidering the vſe of this cuſtome, for more than two hundred yeeres, and innumerable iudgements confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable thereto denounced, to take away all occaſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie and ſtrife, and to ſet downe a written forme for the Iudges vpon all occurrents to proſecute.</p>
            <p>Theſe Lawes, ordinances, and adminiſtrations of iuſtice had beene very well diſcerned, knowen, and obſerued by the former Popes, as well by the continuall informations they haue from the Clergie of this State, as further; by thoſe particularities which they dayly receiued from their Nonci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oes reſident in this Citie; whereas alſo, many Popes haue had full notice and knowledge thereof by themſelues; ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were borne and brought vp in this State, others by hauing liued a priuate life in the ſame, diſcharging there the office of Confeſſors for many yeeres; ſome the office of Inquiſitors, and others hauing beene Biſhops of ſome cities. So that euery Pope hath by ſome meanes had knowledge of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17247:5"/> the equitie and iuſtice of the Venecian lawes, and of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of their Magiſtrates; whereby we may ſuppoſe, that they neuer hauing reclaimed any of them, they haue ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a maner approued of the ſame. Iudgements and arreſts haue euer beene executed vpon Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and in times paſt more often than of late dayes; and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances or lawes aboue written, omitting more ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, haue beene adminiſtred aboue this three hundred yeeres, although now of very late time ſome of them haue been newly confirmed; others more largely extended; and others of vnwritten (which notwithſtanding were obſerued) made written lawes; and finally, are ſo expreſſed and diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Of which, one of the yere 1602, and another of 1603, were peruſed by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth, a moſt zealous and vigilant Paſtor, and yet they could not giue ſatisfaction to this <hi>Paul</hi> the Fift, who thought good, in the beginning of his Papacie, to examine the Lawes and Statutes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>But in the end of October laſt paſt, in an ordinarie audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he complained to the Ambaſſador of this Common-wealth, becauſe in <hi>ſede vacante</hi> they had made a law, which prohibiteth the Clergie to purchaſe any thing ſtable; he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vrging, that though it were inſtituted in the vertue and force of another former, yet that the Canon lawes, both the olde and new, were inualidious; for which cauſe it was his abſolute pleaſure it ſhould be diſanulled, enioyning the Ambaſſador to certifie the Common-wealth of this his will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Who performing as much, and hauing receiued order from the Senate, that he ſhould lay open to the Pope the equitie, iuſtice and reaſons of that law, and of the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue which the Common-wealth had for the making of ſuch ordinances; the Pope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>auing ſtill to his former delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſayd openly, he was content to heare them for their owne ſatisfaction onely, and not to conſider any further of thoſe their allegations; and ſo concluded, that vpon this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17247:5"/> point an hortatorie <hi>Breue</hi> ſhould be directed vnto <hi>Venice,</hi> ſhewing an Excommunication, which he cauſed to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed againſt another City; intimating, how that in ſuch like cauſes he looked not for anſwers or allegation of reaſons, but for a ſpeedy and ready obedience. And he moreouer moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued another complaint for the retention (ſome few moneths before) of a Canon of <hi>Vicenza,</hi> and of the Abbat of <hi>Nerueſa,</hi> alleging how it was his pleaſure, that they ſhould be put o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to the Eccleſiaſticall Court, and that though the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth were priuiledged to iudge Clergie men, yet this did not extend to ſuch maner of perſons, nor to ſuch kinde of offences, for which the two aboue named were impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And heere I thinke it needfull to digreſſe a little, for a declaration of the true cauſe why theſe delinquents were committed to priſon. <hi>Brandolino Valdemarino,</hi> Abbat of <hi>Nerueſa,</hi> was accuſed and complained of for vſing many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall courſes vpon the goods and wiues of certeine men that inhabited in the townes neere about him; that he had killed diuers perſons with poiſon, and amongſt theſe, one religious Prieſt, which was his Curate domeſticall; that he had giuen poiſon to his father and a brother; that he had cauſed diuers men to be ſlaine; that he had continuall and dayly carnall conuerſation with his naturall ſiſter; that hee had vſed many magicall and wicked practiſes to compaſſe his diſhoneſt purpoſes, and for other ends, which can not without horror be more particularly expreſſed; as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the denunciations and complaints made by diuers perſons againſt him. And <hi>Scipio Saracino,</hi> a Canon of <hi>Vicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> was accuſed for hauing contemptuouſly broken vp the publike ſeales of the Rectors of <hi>Vicenza,</hi> ſet vpon the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Chancerie, <hi>ſede vacante,</hi> for the cuſtodie and ſecuritie of the Euidences and Writings of the Biſhopricke, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and requeſt of the Chancellour of the ſame; and moreouer, that he had inſolently caried himſelfe towards a gentlewoman, a widow, of the principalleſt family in all <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenza,</hi> his kinſwoman, by defiling her gate and houſe, after
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17247:6"/> he had a long time, by vndecent meanes, attempted her chaſtitie to the publike ſcandall; for he forbare not to put in practiſe his luxurious diſleignes, euen within the Churches.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the Pope, his H. in diuers meetings with the Ambaſſadour, perſwaded the Common-wealth to lay aſide all their reaſons, and abſolutely to obey him; and after ſome dayes he renewed freſh complaints againſt the law aboue written, which prohibited the building of Churches without licence: and at laſt, he reſolutely came to this point, That he would haue the foreſayd two Lawes reuoked, and the two priſoners deliuered to his Nontio then reſident in <hi>Venice:</hi> wherefore on the tenth of December drawing two <hi>Breues,</hi> one vpon the two lawes, and another vpon ſentence giuen on theſe two Eccleſiaſticks, he enioyned his Nontio to preſent them. But the Nontio (moued thereunto perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture) becauſe the Senate at that time had choſen an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour extraordinarie, to aſſay all milde and poſſible meanes to remoue his holineſſe from this reſolution, which he had vndertaken, before well vnderſtanding of the cauſe; and to induce him, firſt to be better informed, before he proceeded to any other execution; but he deferred the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the <hi>Breue,</hi> this being a thing not well approued of by the Pope: ſo that with all expedition he ſent him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to preſent them immediatly. Wherefore on the day of the Natiuitie of our Lord, when Duke <hi>Grimanni</hi> was euen yeelding vp his ſoule into Gods hands, and that the Signorie with the Senatours were aſſembled, of whom, ſome had alreadie receiued the holy Sacrament of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, others were to receiue it, he requeſted audience, and preſented the two <hi>Breues</hi> ſealed, which were not then ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by reaſon of the Dukes death, which hapned the day following, while after election made of a new. They being at laſt both opened, they both appeared to be of the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame tenor, and implied thus much: How it was giuen him to vnderſtand, that the Common-wealth in her decrees had conſtituted many things againſt the libertie Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17247:6"/> and the authoritie of the See Apoſtolike; and that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſhe had extended thorowout her whole dominion cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine lawes, which concerned only the City of <hi>Venice,</hi> which prohibited the building of Churches, Monaſteries, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious places; and another which forbad the alienation of Lay mens goods to Eccleſiaſticall perſons, without the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates licence. All which things, as being contrarie to the Eccleſiaſticall libertie, he declared as inualidious, and he that inſtituted them had incurred Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, commanding vnder paine, <hi>latae ſententiae,</hi> that they might be reuoked and cancelled, threatning, if he were not herein o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, to proceed further.</p>
            <p>Whereunto the Senate, about the eight and twentieth of Ianurie, made anſwer, That they had with griefe and much woonder vnderſtood by his H. letters, that thoſe lawes, which through ſo many ages had ſo happily beene executed by the Common-wealth, and which by no one of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors were euer reprehended, and which to repeale, would be a turning topſie-turuie of the foundation of their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were now found fault withall, as being contrary to the authoritie of the See Apoſtolike; and ſo they which inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, being men of ſingular pietie, and that deſerued well of the See Apoſtolike, which are in heauen, come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be taxed for Violaters of the Eccleſiaſticall libertie; that they had, according to his H. admonition, examined the lawes, both olde and new, finding nothing in them which might not be decreed by the authoritie of a ſupreame Prince: and touching ſome particulars of their allegations and reaſons, they concluded how in their opinion they had incurred no cenſures; and that his H. repleniſhed with reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and pietie, would not without well vnderſtanding of the cauſe, perſeuere in his comminations and threatnings.</p>
            <p>And heere it is firſt required, that we proceed a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and declare what the obiections are which he makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the two lawes aboue-written, how eaſilie and readilie they may be anſwered; and together, what is the reaſon,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17247:7"/> iuſtice and equitie of theſe lawes, and how lawfull the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Common-wealth is to inſtitute them.</p>
            <p>The Pope obiecteth againſt both theſe lawes together, That they are <hi>ſedis Apoſtolicae auctoritati, &amp; eccleſiaſticae liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati immunitati<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contrariae, tum generalibus Concilijs, &amp; ſacris Canonibus, necnon Romanorum Pontificum conſtitutionibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantes;</hi> wherefore, aboue all other things, it will be very fit, that we vnderſtand what this Eccleſiaſticall libertie is, and from whence it tooke the originall; ſeeing it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that this name is but new, and for twelue ages neuer ſo much as heard of in the Church. The holy Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> makes mention of a Chriſtian libertie, in his Epiſtles to the Romans and Galathians, at full, ſhewing therein, That by the ſinne of our firſt father we were all made ſeruants vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne, from which ſeruitude Chriſt our Lord hath freed vs, we being redeemed by his blood; and therfore he ſaith: <hi>Cùm ſerui eſſetis peccati liberi fuiſtis iuſtitiae, nunc verò liberati a peccato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſerui autem facti Deo, habetis fructum quidem ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationem, finem verò vitam aeternam.</hi> And to the Galathians he propoundeth another ſeruitude to the ceremonies of the Law of Moyſes, from which in like maner Chriſt hath freed vs, when he ſaith:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nunc fratres, non ſumus ancillae filij, ſed libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, qua libertate Chriſtus nos liberauit.</hi> This ſo great grace of libertie was giuen to no others, but to euery one of Chriſtes faithfull, and generally to the body of the Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome of the ancient Saints, called it the libertie of the Church, and none oppoſe themſelues againſt this, except the miniſter of the diuell, and the partakers of hell; and there is no doubt, but whoſoeuer in the leaſt tittle, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to derogate from theſe lawes, but that he ſhould be an alien from the holie Catholike Church. But of this libertie we ſpeake not at this preſent, ſeeing that the famous and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticke name of Church, which anciently was common vnto all the faithfull, as well Clergie as Laietie, ſeemes now to be reſtrained for the moſt part, to ſignifie the Clergy only. Whereupon libertie hath beene granted to it, ſeparate from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17247:7"/> the former, of which, as it appeares, <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third was the firſt that made mention therof, about the yere 1220: but what the ſame <hi>Honorius</hi> vnderſtood by Eccleſiaſtical liberty, and the Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Second, who in the ſame time, and at the inſtance of the ſame Pope nameth it ſo, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they themſelues expreſſe, nor is it yet well decided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Canoniſts: for in all the Canon Law we finde it not determined, neither be theſe things expreſſed which are comprehended vnder the ſame; as alſo there is no rule ſet downe, how to iudge of them: for the which cauſe, when diſputation groweth vpon any point, they do not agree vpon it, what is againſt Eccleſiaſticall libertie. Libertie is defined by the Ciuilians to be a certaine naturall facultie, of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming what one will, as farre as the lawes permit. Some thinke, that this facultie in the Clergie, to doe what they liſt conformable to the lawes, ſhould be the libertie of the Church; ſo that by this meanes, and in that ſenſe, the ſame which is abſolute libertie in the Laie-man, in him of the Clergie it is libertie Eccleſiaſticall, and it conſiſteth in enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that facultie, which common lawes affoord euerie one. It ſeemes this is the meaning of that chap. <hi>Eos qui:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De imm. Eccl. in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> where it is ſaid; that if any man forbid the baking of bread, the grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of corne, or ſuch like ſeruices to be done to the Clergie, this would be preſumed to be done in derogation to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall libertie: Others are not of this opinion, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this title, they comprehend thoſe things which onely concurre with the Clergie, by reaſon of priuiledges granted vnto them by God, or by the Pope in things ſpirituall, and in thoſe temporall by Princes; ſo as by this meanes it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth no other but a priuiledge of exemption granted to the vniuerſall Church, as well in things temporall a, Spirituall.</p>
            <p>An other opinion there is, which comprehendeth theſe two in one: Some call Eccleſiaſticall libertie, whatſoeuer hath beene done in fauour of the Clergie, and they ſay thoſe Statutes are made againſt it, which make the Clergie more feareful, and the Laiety more inſolent, the which is <hi>Bartoloes</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17247:8"/> definition,<note place="margin">Authen. caſſa, C. ſac. ſanct. Eccl.</note> and it appeares to be moſt applied to the exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eccleſiaſticall order.</p>
            <p>Now it is fit we declare, that in which ſoeuer of theſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes you take theſe words, Eccleſiaſticall libertie, the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Venetians Common-wealth, together with the condemnation, and impriſonment of Eccleſiaſticall perſons, infringe no libertie; and withall, we will reſolue ſuch obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are particularly made againſt any of thoſe lawes.</p>
            <p>The Pope alleadgeth no other ſpeciall reaſon why the law of prohibition to build Churches, is offenſiue, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it was inſtituted; for ſo be the formall words of his <hi>Breue: Quaſi Eccleſiae, &amp; Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiaſticae perſonae temporali vestrae iuriſdictioni ſubiectae aliquo modo eſſent, vel qui ea rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one in veſtris ditionibus Eccleſias, &amp; alia pia ac religioſa loca extruerent, tanquam in aliquo ſcelere deprehenſi mulctandi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither in like manner, doth he alledge any other reaſon to prooue his intention, that the prohibiting of the Laietie not to bequeath or giue in perpetuall, &amp; not to alienate any thing ſtable to the Clergie, is againſt the libertie Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but that it ſeemes it is grounded vpon a certaine vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped iuriſdiction, which the Secular power hath ouer Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall goods; and theſe be his words: <hi>Perinde ac ſi tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus dominis liceret in Eccleſiastica bona, quae Ecclesijs, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perſonis, &amp; alijs locis pijs, à teſtatoribus, &amp; caeteris Chriſti fidelibus, pro remedio peccatorum, &amp; exoneratione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> relinquuntur, aut alio modo conferuntur, ius ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod exercere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But firſt of all, any one that ſhall but diligently conſider, will of himſelfe conceiue, that to make a law which prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth euery body, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Laie, to build no Churches without licence, is not (as the Pope obiecteth) to exerciſe a power ouer the Church; but rather ouer the ground, floare, or ſuperficiall part, where one may build; which no man can denie to be purely and meerely ſecular. No priuate man that ſhould forbid an Eccleſiaſticall perſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17247:8"/> to build a Church vpon his ground, could be ſaid to ordaine any thing againſt the Church, or any Eccleſiaſticall perſon; but that he may diſpoſe of his owne ground at his pleaſure, and forbid the vſe of a thing, which he is not bound by the law to permit or graunt. That which may be built, is not called a Church; but that which is readie dedicated: euerie priuate man hath power ouer his owne freehold, and the Prince hath a greater power ouer all the ground and free-holds of his dominion. Wherefore as it would be iniuſtice to build a Church vpon any priuate mans ground without his permiſſion; no leſſe an iniuſtice it were to do as much in what place ſoeuer belonging to a Prince, contrary to his prohibition: In neither of theſe conſtructions is the libertie Eccleſiaſticall infringed: not in the former caſe; becauſe no man hath libertie to vſe that of an other mans, againſt the owners will: and in the ſecond in like maner; becauſe God the vniuerſall Lord of all things, giuing libertie to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church to build Temples, he doth not in this take away priuate power and dominion, nor yet the Princes empire and prerogatiue ouer the ſoile; neither did the Pope otherwiſe at any time, nor he cannot diſpoſe of the ſame, being a thing temporall; and no Prince could euer with his priuiledge diſpoſe of any thing in the State of this Common-wealth, which was born free; and ſo in no reſpect there is no derogation heerein from Eccleſiaſticall libertie.</p>
            <p>For if this reaſon were preualent, The Church is a ſpiritual thing; wherefore he which diſpoſeth of the building of the ſame, goes about to diſpoſe of a thing ſpirituall: it would follow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rouen,</hi> a kinde of oakes.</note> that a Prince that ſhould prohibite to put oakes or timbers into the building of Churches, which likewiſe ſerue to build gallies, ſhips, bridges, and for other vſes; or that through ſcarcitie ſhould forbid to couer them with lead, for which he had more neceſſarie vſe in the wars, he might be ſaid to make a law againſt the Churches, and the couering of them, it being notwithſtanding true, that his ordinance is but vpon timbers and lead, which are meerely temporall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17247:9"/> things. What is it I pray you which may not be dedicated vnto diuine worſhip? Why ſurely nothing; for ſinne onely being oppoſite and contrarie vnto God, all other things may be conſecrated vnto him. He therfore that diſpoſeth of a thing by forbidding it not to be dedicated; ſhall he in this offend God? No queſtionleſſe.</p>
            <p>For the commandements of diuine honor being affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, comprehends not all matter, all places, all times, as they would haue them to doe that wring euery thing to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall behoofe; but he permitteth, after nothing is wanting to his ſeruice, that the reſt be applied to humane vſes, and that there may be aſcribed to himſelfe, what is apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decent and fit.</p>
            <p>If it were lawfull againſt a Princes will to build a Church in any place, it would be in like maner lawfull to vſe any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or what workeman ſoeuer; the which extending euen to the furniture and ornaments of the Churches, and of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred implements, it would follow that euery cloth, all met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, wood, or any other thing, ſhould belong vnto the State Eccleſiaſtical: the abſurdity of which conſequences do euidently declare, that as the Church being once dedicated, it perteineth then to the Spiritualty; ſo no place can be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, without the permiſſion of the Temporall Prince: and the equitie of this law hath euer beene apparently knowne vnto the world.<note place="margin">L. ſacra §. <hi>1.</hi> ff. de re diuiſ. L. ſi plures ſint &amp; l. <hi>2</hi> ff. de rel. q. &amp; ſum. fun. L. vlt. ff. un. in poſ. legael.</note> 
               <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Oration <hi>pro domo ſua,</hi> ſheweth, that in thoſe daies no man could conſecrate an altar, <hi>iniuſſu populi.</hi> Vnder the heathen Emperours alſo, there were foure lawes which forbad the conſecration of any thing without the Princes leaue; which <hi>Iustinian</hi> hauing placed amongſt the <hi>Digeſta,</hi> out of doubt he hath adapted them to our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and giuen them vigor alſo ouer the building of our Churches: and whoſoeuer ſhal read the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> his Nouels, will finde, that in the Emperours daies, as well in the Eaſt as in the Weſt, it hath in this point beene referred to the Prince aboue all others; ſo that their licence and fauour was euer requeſted to build new Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17247:9"/> and further, that not any did euer ſo much as thinke of the building of a Metropolitan or Cathedrall Church, without the expreſſe decree and permiſſion of the Prince. Vpon this point we may peruſe the 27 Nouell of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> and that which <hi>Balſamo</hi> very copiouſly relateth vpon the 17 Canon in the Councell of <hi>Calcedon.</hi> And here it will not be much from the purpoſe, to adde the cuſtome of <hi>France,</hi> where they can not build any Churches without expreſſe grant by the Kings Letters-patents; and moreouer, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or Act of Parliament. And further, to ſet downe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſome place in <hi>Italie,</hi> we haue it here recorded, that in the Common-wealth of <hi>Genoa,</hi> there is a particular conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, that without the licence of both the Colleges, they can not build any Monaſteries, vnder penaltie of confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the place.</p>
            <p>But the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> neuer caſt her eye ſo much vpon the materiall Churches, as on the perſons which were to gouerne them; for euery Order of religious men befit not any place. We haue an excellent example of this in the famous gouernment of the Kings of <hi>Caſtilia,</hi> where, without the Kings licence, no new religious Orders can haue any entrance into thoſe Kingdomes; and therefore euen at this preſent the Cappuchine Friers could neuer be thither admitted. And there are not many yeeres paſt ſince the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>S. Francis</hi> of <hi>Paula</hi> began to build a Church in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dril,</hi> without the Kings permiſſion; which worke King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the ſecond made ſtay of, the Church it ſelfe yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for an example, it being begun, and not finiſhed. And your holineſſe hauing ſometimes beene Nontio extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie to that King, may peraduenture haue ſeene the ſame.</p>
            <p>The foundations of this decree are no leſſe equall, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and lawfull, than moſt neceſſarie; for as it would not in any wiſe be permitted to a great number of a ſtrange State, contrarie in their cuſtomes of life, and hauing diuers ends from thoſe of a Common-wealth, to enter into the State of ſuch a Common-wealth, to gather themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17247:10"/> into one place, to make amongſt them an head, and in ſecret to practiſe with the Princes ſubiects; ſeeing this would be preſently interrupted as a ſuſpitious and pernitious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticle: So vnder pretext of ſome new Monaſterie, many of other nations ſometimes may come in together vnder an head, they being contrarie in cuſtomes and affections, and by the opportunitie they haue, through Confeſſions or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirituall conferences, inſinuating with the Princes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, they may by this meanes corrupt them in their fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: this in like maner, for many excellent cauſes, is dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be looked vnto, for the publike preſeruation and peace of the State; and euen for this very reſpect it greatlie concerned the Common-wealth to diſmiſſe certaine Fathers of a Monaſterie, all of them being of ſtrange nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe diuers men of the Arſenall were ſeduced by them. And thus we may ſee, that the Oratories and Monaſteries in a Citie which conſiſt all of one Nation, eſpecially when they are repleniſhed with diuers ſorts of men, can not be enterteined without notable danger, if the Prince be not alwayes made priuie with what paſſeth amongſt them in their aſſemblies. Vnto this may further be annexed, that buildings which are not ſituated in conuenient places, they bring great dammage vnto Cities, and eſpecially to thoſe which are ſtrong and fortified: and it is well knowen how many Cities haue diuers times beene loſt, by meanes of a Church built without the walles, not farre from the Towne ditch, when it hath come into the enemies hands there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped: as alſo in like maner, what hurt ſuch a building nere vnto the walles within hath procured: and ſo what a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of aedifices and erections, for important reſpects, haue beene raſed and pluckt downe for publike ſecuritie, to the no ſmall woonder (ſometimes) of deuout and ignorant perſons.</p>
            <p>It is not only profitable for publike good, as hath aboue beene ſhewed, that Churches ſhould not be built without licence; but further, it is requiſit for the Churches them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17247:10"/> to the end that any man, at his owne will and pleaſure, may not erect them in vndecent places, neere to publicke Stewes or common Neceſſaries; nor of vnſeemly forme, or without the conuenient <hi>decorum</hi> due vnto the maieſty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; ſo as they might ſerue rather for deriſion, than any thing els. And we ſee, that the great and ſuperabundant number of Churches is not profitable for deuotion, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite contrarie; for when they are too many, due ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can not be diſcharged to all; and one Church ill ſerued, procureth more indeuotion, than tenne well employed can preuent: as alſo, the almes ſufficeth not for all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when the number of them exceedeth; ſo as neither the old nor the new haue their requiſit cures.</p>
            <p>Through Gods grace and fauour there want not Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and other holy places in the Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> and in all others ſubiect to that State; and theſe ſuch and ſo many, that ſome Cities repleniſhed with the reliques of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Martyrs, ſcarſe decently preſerued, may take an example from them: and yet for all this, the Senate neuer forbare, when conuenient opportunitie was offered, to giue licence for the building of new Churches and religious places, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it fell out fit; and in like maner, to admit ingreſſe to new religious Orders, after the enacting of the ſayd law.</p>
            <p>But who will not maruell, when he ſhall heare the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Venetian law, impoſed vpon him which buildeth Churches without licence, reprehended; it being obiected by the Oppoſer, That to build them is in it ſelfe no wicked act? As though a worke of his owne nature, and in it ſelfe good, if it be performed without due circumſtances, is not vicious and deſerueth chaſtiſement. Not from the matter or obiect only (ſayth <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and after him,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ethic. c.</hi> 6.</note> all the Diuines) is an action conſtrued, but from the integritie of all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. It is good to build Churches in place, time, and maner conuenient: but without theſe conditions it is not good to build a Church on another mans ground; neither is it iuſt, without the owners conſent. Beſides the dominion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17247:11"/> which euery priuate man hath, a Prince hath a farre greater power ouer all places, to whom both the owner and the place it ſelfe is ſubiect; ſo as we may not do with them what the Prince prohibiteth and conſents not to.</p>
            <p>Out of queſtion, I haue ſpent many more words heerein than was requiſite, that euery one (if he haue but common ſenſe) may conceiue the reaſons and occaſions of this law: but I repent me not hereof, becauſe they may alſo ſerue for a defence of that law of 1605, which prohibiteth the Laitie to alienate any thing ſtable to Eccleſiaſticks. For this doth leſſe diſpoſe of any thing of the Church, neither impoſeth it any thing vpon Eccleſiaſticall perſons, but only vpon Seculars and Secular mens goods. What iniurie ſhall a Prince offer in this, when he commandeth his ſubiects to haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with ſome kinde of perſons? The prohibiting of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren tranſportations, or to bring in all kinde of merchandize, is an vſuall thing in all Kingdoms: is it therefore an iniurie to ſtrangers? I thinke no man will ſubſcribe to this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; and ſo much the rather, by how much priuate men make ſuch a law vpon their owne goods, when in contracts liuellarie they ſet downe conditions,<note place="margin">When one builds vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other mans floore.</note> that the liuellaries ſhall not ſell or alienate his goods to the Church: and yet euerie one doth this. And others in their Teſtaments, to keepe their goods in their houſe, they deuiſe couenants, that it may neuer paſſe ouer to the Church. All lawes <hi>de fide commiſſa</hi> would be againſt the liberty Eccleſiaſticall, becauſe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the making ouer of any goods to the Church, and thoſe of <hi>Falcidia Trebellianica</hi> alſo, becauſe they all detaine that portion from the Church, which being taken from the lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, they would haue then remained vnto the true heire.</p>
            <p>I know that ſome one very deſirous of the augmentation of Eccleſiaſticall rights in the Temporaltie will affirme, that ſo it is; but I beleeue his opinion will haue but a few follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and it is a great wilfulneſſe, to condemne actions and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which all Chriſtendome, from a thouſand fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and more yeeres ſince, hath not onely (I will not ſay)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17247:11"/> admitted; but further, praiſed, commended, and thought them ſeruiceable vnto God.</p>
            <p>There are indeed ſome, who in fauour of the Secular may ſay, That it had beene, and would yet be very lawfull, to conſtitute a law, that none might ſell their ſtable poſſeſſion without licence: which generall caueat would alſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Eccleſiaſticks: and the Prince, being ſued vnto for licence, might readily grant it, when the alienation were to paſſe ouer to a Lay man; and ſo to denie it vpon the demiſe to an Eccleſiaſticke; and this would not be againſt libertie Eccleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>To whom we muſt anſwer with ſome libertie, for if they would a little looke ouer their Logicke, they ſhould finde that the whole <hi>genus</hi> being granted, euerie <hi>ſpecies</hi> in priuate and particular is yeelded vnto: ſo that whoſoeuer grants, that a Prince may abſolutely prohibite any alienation, he muſt needs likewiſe confeſſe, that hee may prohibite it in Strangers, Noble-men, Eccleſiaſtickes, or in whatſoeuer kinde of other perſons in particular. They ſay he may doe this abſolutely to all; but ſo not to the Clergie alone: and the Logician ſaies; he may vniuerſally to all; and therefore alſo to the Eccleſiaſticall in particular.</p>
            <p>But yet we will ſpeake vnto them ſomewhat more ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and aduiſe them to ſtudie a little the holy Scriptures, where S. <hi>Paul</hi> will teach them: <hi>Nolite errare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Deus non irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur:</hi> A goodly matter certainly. If this be no ſinne to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that lay goods may not be paſſed ouer to eccleſiaſtical perſons, why do they condemne it? why reprehend they it? Hath not the Prince done well enough, in no waies offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God; and if it be ſinne, when the ſame effect remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the words are but onely changed; what haue they done elſe in this, but ieſted with God, and thought to deceiue him with Sophiſtications? It is not Gods pleaſure that ſuch like thoughts ſhould euer come into a Chriſtian mans heart. If it were Gods will, that the Clergie ordained by him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Spirituall things; &amp; allowing this inſtitution, that they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17247:12"/> ſhould be made owners, not onely of a part of Temporall things, but euen of all; we ought not then to honour them with words onely, but euen with deeds to procure alſo, that aſſoone as poſſible, this his diuine will might be effected.</p>
            <p>But let vs proceed to declare more perſpicuouſly, that a Prince by ſuch a law ordaineth but truly of his owne things, and not of thoſe of the Church. This is moſt manifeſt, that if any ſeruice lie vpon a poſſeſſion or tenure, the owner of the ſame cannot paſſe it ouer ſo to the Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as that this ſeruice and bond may be fruſtrate: but whatſoeuer poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtable there is in a State, it oweth ſubiection to the Prince, the which is greater and much more ſtrict then can any waies belong to a priuate man; for the power of a Prince ouer all goods, is farre greater then is the prerogatiue of a priuate man. A Prince by his power for publike good, may extenuate and vtterly take away a priuate right; but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Lord can in no wiſe derogate or take away from the power of a Prince: for euen by his will and gift, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes he cannot procure but that a Prince will haue his interreſt therein. Let euery one but weigh and conſider how conformable to nature it would be, that any thing ſhould paſſe by the diſpoſition of a priuate man vnto the Church, and that for this cauſe it ſhould be free from ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to the Prince. But they will anſwer: they are content it ſhould be conueied ouer with bond and obligation, to pay all ſuch duties as it was charged withall in the Lay man. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good; but why at this preſent doe they conſent heereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and in times paſt they would be exempted from all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant and bond. And yet moreouer we may affirme, that a Prince hath other right ouer all ſtable goods, beſides ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie tributes; ſeeing he may challenge extraordinarie du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties alſo in the ſame, without the which couenant, it is not reaſon it ſhould be conueied ouer, becauſe as well as the others, he may taxe it with other impoſitions. And if this ſeeme ſomewhat a hard condition, yet is it but naturall. But further yet; if the Prince challenge ſome perſonall ſeruices
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17247:12"/> from the poſſeſſors, as in the warres, offices, Court atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, or any other reſpect; why ſhould he loſe it? and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, the Prince hath <hi>ius,</hi> to confiſcate that ſtable poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion for the Lords offence; but being paſſed ouer to the Church, it is not then confiſcable; and therefore why ſhould the Prince loſe his <hi>ius?</hi> and heere occurreth a moſt notable example to conuince theſe opponents.</p>
            <p>Eccleſiaſticall Benefices are voide by the death of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, and therefore the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the firſt fruits, and the price of the <hi>Bolle.</hi> Many Benefices belonging to Monaſteries, Chapters, and other Fraternities, the Popes perceiuing that by ſuch a dependence they loſt that benefit, which otherwiſe by the Curats death came vnto their hands, and they conſidered that vnder euery fifteene yeeres, ſuch a vacancie might haue fallen out; and therefore they ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that all Benefices thus depending, ſhould pay euerie fifteene yeeres a fifteene. So in like maner may a Prince ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that vnder euery hundred of yeeres, a poſſeſſion may come to be confiſcated, and ſo make them pay euery hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres a valuable confiſcation.</p>
            <p>To preuent which, in ſome kingdomes there is a cuſtome that when any thing ſtable is conueied ouer to the Church, the ſame is bound to giue <hi>homine viuente moriente,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcabile,</hi> till the ſtabilitie be by royall authoritie extinct.<note place="margin">Euery fifteene a fifteenth, &amp; once in an hundred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcable value.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Stable poſſeſſion alſo, is oftentimes ſold, and paieth for the ſame ſome duties to the Prince, or goeth to ſtrange heires, for which likewiſe a certaine portion is paid: as in like maner, if after the terme of many yeeres, one of theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents ſhould occurre, would it be reaſon that the Prince without any conſent giuen thereunto, ſhould be depriued of theſe his rights? And therefore the Statute of 1605 is verie iuſt and iuridiall: and if together with licence for the reaſons aboue alledged, there were a peculiar dutie paide vpon the conueiance ouer of any thing ſtable to the Church, it would not be vniuſt; for in <hi>France</hi> and many other kingdomes, when any thing is paſſed ouer with licence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17247:13"/> to the Church, they pay a third part, as they ſay, amortiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, for the poſſeſſion ſtable, which now lieth dead as it were to the Prince, who hath no profit nor ſeruice from it as before. There is nothing therefore committed againſt iuſtice and equitie, if the Prince ſeeing himſelfe to loſe ſo many royalties, and perceiuing the Clergie to enioy twenty times ſo much as they may well content themſelues with, deliberate and reſolue to ſtay their hands, and to permit no further purchaſe without licence: the which notwithſtanding he may grant them when it ſhall be conuenient. Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of confiſcation, ſale, and legacie vnto ſtrangers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring alſo with the ground or ſuperficies where any deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to build Churches; no wonder though a Prince per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not, that his royaltie therein be amortizate without his licence. But proceeding yet ſomewhat further; they which denie a ſecular Prince this prerogatiue, to make lawes vpon Eccleſiaſticall goods, or that Eccleſiaſticall perſons ſhould be ſubiect to ſecular lawes, they neuertheleſſe conſent to this, that any kinde of lawes may be inſtituted to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend within them alſo the Clergie. But publike good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that this moſt principall member of a Common-wealth ſhould be preſerued, which is, the part Secular, in that it beares all burdens, performeth publike actions, as well reall, as perſonall, to the end, that fall not out where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Vlpiano</hi> ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">ff. de mune &amp; bon. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quòd viribus deſtituta erit Reſpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</hi> This law therefore is iuſt, and it is but conuenient, that this member ſhould be protected by the Prince, ſo that his owne good and treaſure being preſerued in the ſame, it may retaine neceſſarie force to ſerue the Common-wealth: &amp; if it grow from this, that the Eccleſiaſticks haue leſſe then they ſhould haue; this comes not directly from the Prince, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accidentally occurreth; and the lawes or iuſtice hath neuer reſpect to that which inſueth indirectly or by accident: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhet is it preſumed, he doth iniurie his neighbour that hath only reference to his owne peculiar profit, although it may wel grow therupon, that his companion is depriued of ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17247:13"/> gaine, which otherwiſe he might haue made to himſelfe.<note place="margin">l. ſi quis ne cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam ff. ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert. pet. c. quia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitatem de conceſ. praeb.</note> I confeſſe, if this law were not, the Church indeed might be more enriched; but iniunctiue charitie and God commands vs, that euery one ſhould firſt regard thoſe things moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for himſelfe, and that is, to follow his vocation. He that preſerues his owne, preſerues it out of doubt from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into another mans hands; and one neuer growes rich, but another is the poorer for it: and yet it is not againſt the rule of charitie to preuent our owne pouertie, becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we hinder another mans enriching. A Prince muſt haue a care, that the peace and power of his Empire be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined.</p>
            <p>And if from hence it come, that the Clergies allowance ſhall not augment, the Prince muſt not haue an eye to that. <hi>Gaietan,</hi> who was followed by diuers others,<note place="margin">In Summa ner. excom. c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> denieth that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſtatute to be againſt Eccleſiaſticall libertie, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth and moderates the expence of Funerals, Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and new Maſſes; and yet it manifeſtly proceeds heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, that the Clergie are by this meanes depriued of thoſe gaines, which otherwiſe they ſhould enioy, if all exceſſe were lawfull.</p>
            <p>If the Clergie would buy or purchaſe,<note place="margin">12. <hi>q.</hi> 2.</note> with what money ſhall they buy or purchaſe? The granted Canon commands, that the Eccleſiaſticall reuenew ſhould be diſtributed into foure parts; the firſt for the Biſhop, the ſecond for the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies maintenance, the third for building, and the fourth for almes to the poore: the which was alſo confirmed by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, in his Capitolar.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 87.</note> The Clergie certeinly would not purchaſe with the firſt or ſecond part; and it is not conuenient to take away neceſſarie maintenance: to let old buildings go to the ground to buy new, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and it would be againſt publike good; and to imploy therein the fourth part, which belongeth to the poore, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will not ſuffer, nor the ſaying of our Lord, ſeeing <hi>S. Paul</hi> commands vs to haue alwayes in remembrance, <hi>Beatiùs est dare, quàm accipere.</hi> Wherefore returning to poſſeſſions left
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17247:14"/> or bequeathed, we muſt obſerue, that by this law the Church is not denied to holde all that which is giuen or bequeathed vnto it; the which, though they haue not in proper kinde, yet haue they the price, which is equall to the thing.</p>
            <p>It would peraduenture be from our purpoſe, to adde hereunto, but very briefly, that it would be as euill, as profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, for the Clergie to poſſeſſe ſuperfluouſly; for by this meanes they haue forſaken Gods ſeruice, which they haue in charge to proſecute; and in the Eccleſiaſticall lawes there is an whole title to this effect:<note place="margin">In decretal.</note> 
               <hi>Ne Clerici, vel Monaci ſecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus negotijs ſe immiſceant:</hi> where it ſeemes, that the firſt chapter was particularly made to prohibit theſe preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> and <hi>S. Paul</hi> in a few words commandeth; <hi>Nemo militans Deo, implicat ſe negotijs ſecularibus, vt ei placeat cui ſe probauit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Matth. hom. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> There is a long diſcourſe of <hi>S. Iohn Chryſostome,</hi> wherein he ſheweth, That two maine inconueniences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the riches of the Church; one, That the Laitie by that meanes ceaſe from giuing of almes; and another, That Clergie men, leauing their cures, which is the cure of ſoules, they become Proctors, Economiſts, and Tole-gatherers, practiſing things vnbeſeeming their Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>The Clergie ſometimes with grieuous complaints doe vrge, That they are forbidden that which is permitted to all other ſorts of men, euen vnto the vileſt and moſt infamous; as if they were of worſer qualitie than they. To which we may anſwer: Firſt, that euery thing is not conuenient for euery body: and it is no conſequent, though one thing be granted vnto others, that therefore it ſhould be permitted them alſo. Souldiers and Gentlemen are ſuffered to goe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; ſhould the ſame be likewiſe permitted vnto them? And the ſame not being granted, may they iuſtly eſteeme themſelues herein iniuried, and that they are worſe intreated than all others? when if any body in the Common-wealth poſſeſſe more than his part, it is conuenient he ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe no more.<note place="margin">Nouell. extrau.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantinus, Porfirogenitus, Romanus</hi> &amp; <hi>Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> Emperors of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> made laws, that the Patritians
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17247:14"/> and Senators, Biſhops and Monaſteries, might purchaſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their inferiors by ſale, donation, or teſtament, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that neceſſary member of the Common wealth: and ſo may the Senat make another law vpon the goods of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, conuenient for their good gouernment, when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: and ſo they haue done vpon Eccleſiaſtical perſons at this preſent, becauſe the bodie of the Common wealth muſt be kept in ſuch temper, to the end that any one member ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not his due proportion, &amp; that the bodie by this means become monſtrous; and taking to it ſelfe more nouriſhment than is requiſit, it may preiudice the other members, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridging them of their allowance; and ſo of it ſelfe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to digeſt this ſuperfluitie, it comes to be poſſeſſed with euill humors, whereupon, firſt infirmitie groweth to it ſelfe, and afterwards corruption to the whole bodie. But the Eccleſiaſticall State in this dominion, is a member which may be thought to be an hundred part of the whole number of inhabitants, and yet hath drawen vnto it ſelfe a portion of the goods, not proportionable to the ſame: for in the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of <hi>Padoa</hi> they haue more than a third part; in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of <hi>Bergamo</hi> more than the halfe: and there is no place where they doe not enioy at leaſt a fourth of the goods and wealth; and if they were ſuffered yet ſtill to purchaſe, there is no doubt, but in time they would be Lords of the whole countrey, leauing all others poore and naked, yea, euen ſlaues, and cutting off the Seculars from all ſuſtentation and nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>The time and place preſent require a law, which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit ſuch an exceſſe. In ancient times, when the State Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticke was gouerned after the ſame maner as the bleſſed Apoſtles inſtituted it, and the holie Fathers after their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples proſecuted the ſame, it was then very profitable that it ſhould poſſeſſe much; and in the bodie of the Common-wealth it was like the ſtomacke, which receiued indeed all the meat, but ſo it digeſted little for it ſelfe, and much for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And thus the Clergie poſſeſſing much, and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17247:15"/> but ſparinglie of the profit of the incomes it ſelfe, but diſtributing all the remainder in almes deeds, they were very emolumentall to the Common-wealth: for the which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo, euery one laboured to powre vpon them goods and poſſeſſions, becauſe the more they had, the more it redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to publike vtilitie and profit, in which the Eccleſiaſticks were Gardians, and Procurers for the poore and needie; ſo that from this no monſtruoſitie was deriued, goods Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall being as common goods, which gaue nouriſhment and increaſe to all the whole bodie proportionablie, and not to one part alone. But this laudable cuſtome now being come to an end, the ſubſtance and goods conueyed ouer to the Church, ſurmount in meaſure and equalitie; and this is too diſproportionable for the body of the Common-wealth, which would finde a great diſcommoditie, if it ſhould fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther augment: neither could it be well gouerned, but of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity either it muſt be reduced to his true meaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, or els the ruine of the whole bodie muſt ſucceed. And though we haue ſpoken of Eccleſiaſticall goods, as common to them all, yet is not the poſſeſſion thereof e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallie diuided amongſt them; nay, and which is more, the fourths of the Religious liue not vpon the Church reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, but vpon almes, and ſecular mens deuotions; the poſſeſſions and reuenewes lying in the hands of a few of the Clergie, which ſcarſely amount to the fourth part of them. And that which more importeth, is, that the moitie of theſe inhabit out of the State, and yet theſe hale vnto themſelues all the reuenewes, with moſt euident loſſe and preiudice to publike ſeruices and emploiments.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ad fra. in er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. ſer. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note>And if in better times, when men thought more on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen than on the world, and when the Auguſtines flouriſhed, who refuſed ſuch inheritance as was left vnto the Church, by depriuing of their owne children, there was ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe made; what would fall out in theſe our after dayes, there now liuing a number, who with deuices and deceits la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſtill; for out of doubt it is to be feared, that in two or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17247:15"/> three hundred yeeres, their purchaſe will grow to that height, as they will become Lords ouer all. There are Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries which haue beene now built this three hundred yeeres, and yet haue they not the fourth part of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes which ſome haue that were built within theſe fortie yeeres. Now there are diuers Religious orders, which are prohibited to poſſeſſe any thing ſtable; the which if it were remooued, which in probabilitie might eaſily be done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſee as much done by foure moſt numerous orders, beſides ſome other minors; let any man that hath iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but imagine, what purchaſe in a moment would be made.</p>
            <p>Many things in their beginnings haue beene good, which altering with time become moſt pernicious. The purchaſe of the Clergie men, which was excellent in the beginning, is fallen by foure degrees, vnto this preſent State: Firſt,<note place="margin">Act....</note> the poſſeſſions were ſold, and the Clergie and poore were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined of the price: Afterwards they ſtudied how to retaine the freehold, and to mainteine the poore of the incomes: Thirdly, there was diſtribution made of it, into foure parts; one for the Biſhop, the ſecond for the Clergie,<note place="margin">c. futurum &amp;c......</note> the third for the building, the fourth for the poore. Now there is a ſtaie of the profits, and an opinion ſtart vp, which by all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines &amp; good Canoniſts, was euer reiected: that,<note place="margin">c. conceſſo.</note> 
               <hi>Clerici ſunt Domini fructuum:</hi> although the ſacred Canons and holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue euer conſtantly preached, that the Eccleſiaſticall goods belonged to the poore: For which cauſe alſo the ſacred Councell of <hi>Trent: Omnino interdicit Epiſcopis, ne ex reditibus Eccleſiae, conſanguineos, familiare ſue ſuos augere ſtude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, cùm &amp; Apoſtolorum Canones prohibeant, ne res Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas, quae Dei ſunt, conſanguineis donent. Sed ſi pauperes ſint, ijs vt pauperibus diſtribuant.</hi> And a little vnderneath; <hi>Quae ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò de Epiſcopis dicta ſunt, eadem non ſolùm in quibuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia Eccleſiaſtica tam ſaecularia, quàm regularia obtinentibus pro gradus ſui conditione obſeruari, ſed ad S. R. E. Cardinales per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere decernit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17247:16"/>
            <p>And Eccleſiaſticks ſhould not ſo ſiniſterly interpret a law made for a publike neceſſitie, it being ſo conformable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and iuſtice, and ſay that it was made to make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors to baſe and illiberall men: they might rather haue ſaid, it would be farre better that they would liue conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Apoſtles. But will they then peraduenture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</note> that the Apoſtles themſelues ſelling all their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; diſtributing them to the poore, were of worſer quality and condition then the moſt infamous ſort of men? Shall ſo many fraternities of Regulars, which poſſeſſe nothing, be reputed infamous or vile? And if they anſwer that they doe thus voluntarily, it may be replied, that voluntarie or not voluntarie, make ſome difference indeed, about the being meritorious or vertuous, but not about the being honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or baſe: For this purpoſe there is a Canon worthie of conſideration,<note place="margin">De conſec. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. <hi>1.</hi> c. vaſa.</note> wherein it is ſaid: <hi>Bonifacius martyr &amp; Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus interrogatus ſi liceret in vaſculis ligneis ſacramenta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere, reſpondit, quondam ſacerdotes aurei ligneis calicibus vtebantur, nunc è contrario lignei ſacerdotes aureis vtuntur ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let them be contented willingly with that which they haue, which is ſo far aboue their ſhare; and ſo we ſhal quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be at a point. The example of <hi>Moyſes</hi> is worthy of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in chap. 36 of <hi>Exodus,</hi> who hauing exhorted the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to offer vp gold, ſiluer, and other precious things for the building of the Temple, when there was more offered then was conuenient, he appointed by a publike proclamation, that no body ſhould offer any more. And we may adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all this, an other reaſon alſo; If by theſe lawes the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall libertie were infringed; then by the Lawes Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call alſo, which prohibite the Eccleſiaſticks to alienate any thing to Seculars, the Secular libertie ſhould be iniuried, and by this meanes they might make Lawes, to take away other mens libertie, and they might not doe the like againe vnto them: and this reaſon is ſo much the more preualent, in that Laie poſſeſſions though they might not be paſſed ouer to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17247:16"/> the Clergie, yet the price thereof might be conueied, and with licence the goods themſelues by a iuſt ſale; but the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks can not alienate vpon any gratuite bargaine whatſoeuer, nor ſell, nor change, but with good gaine and aduantage; and if the Seculars which haue more reaſon, complaine not of this, why ſhould they grieuouſly complain for a matter of farre leſſe conſequence? I will finiſh this point with this ſaying; That before the yeere 400 of our ſauing health, <hi>Valentinian, Valent,</hi> and <hi>Gratian</hi> made a Law;<note place="margin">C. Theod. de ep. &amp; cler. l. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> That the Clergie might not purchaſe any thing of women; the which law was alſo put in vre by Saint <hi>Damaſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe daies when it was publiſhed, it being openly proclaimed, and alſo for a long time after it was obſerued in <hi>Rome;</hi> and S. <hi>Ierome</hi> who makes mention of it in his Epiſtle to <hi>Nepotianus,</hi> ſaith, he found no fault with the law, becauſe the Clergie had worthily deſerued it; but onely he grieued at their auarice, which had giuen Princes iuſt occaſion to make ſuch an one. There was ſuch a like law alſo made in <hi>Saxonie</hi> by <hi>Charlemaine</hi> of famous memorie, which was long obſerued and kept. In the yeere 1300,<note place="margin">Polyd. l. <hi>13.</hi> Hiſt. Anglicae.</note> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> the Third King of <hi>England,</hi> made a law preciſely conformable to this, and though the Clergie reſiſted, yet was it for all that put in execution.<note place="margin">De cont. t. d. <hi>2. 140.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> t. <hi>8.</hi> §.</note> 
               <hi>Lodouicke Molina</hi> teſtifieth in the ordinances of <hi>Portugall,</hi> that there was a law made; that Churches and Monaſteries might not, either by ſale, donation, or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, purchaſe any thing ſtable, to the end that Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reuenues and poſſeſſions might not immeaſurablie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, to the preiudice of the Laietie; he further adding, that in other kingdomes of <hi>Spaine</hi> alſo the ſame law was in force. Certaine it is,<note place="margin">Petr. Bolug. in ſpe princ. R. <hi>13.</hi> C.</note> that <hi>Iames</hi> king of <hi>Arragon</hi> conſtituted in the kingdomes ſubiect to that Crowne, that <hi>Realenco</hi> goods (for ſo they tearme them which hold in <hi>capite,</hi> or pay any thing to the King) might not be demized ouer to the Clergie without the Kings licence. In <hi>France</hi> the ſame law was enacted by S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> which was a ſtrange matter, and afterwards ſucceſſiuely confirmed by <hi>Philip</hi> the Third; <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17247:17"/> the Faire,<note place="margin">Hen. <hi>17.</hi> c.</note> by <hi>Charles</hi> the Faire, by <hi>Charles</hi> the Fift, by <hi>Frances</hi> the Firſt, by <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, by <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth, and by <hi>Henry</hi> the Third. And yet the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> now three hundred yeeres ſince, hauing made the ſame law for her Citie and Duchie, we can ſay no leſſe, but that the extention of the ſame ouer her whole State and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, is an innouation, ſeeing <hi>Saluius Guilianus</hi> anſwers; <hi>Omnes debere ſequileges &amp; conſuetudines vrbis Romae,</hi> as the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> reporteth;<note place="margin">C. de vet. iur. enuel. §. ſed etſi.</note> And in <hi>Sicilia</hi> the yeere 1296 King <hi>Fredericke</hi> (as it is written in the Capitular of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) made a law of the ſelfe ſame forme that the ſame of <hi>Venice</hi> is, in the yeere 1536, but that it giues the reſpite but of a yeere onely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> in like maner in the towne of <hi>Boſco,</hi> where he was borne, hauing built there a great Monaſterie, becauſe the towne might not come to decay, he prohibited for euer the Clergie, to buie any thing of the Laietie: and <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight perceiuing how much the houſe of <hi>Loreto</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, for preſeruation to the Laietie, he forbad them to buie any more. And in <hi>Genoa</hi> alſo, there is a generall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, that all goods ſhould be tied to the Common-wealth, ſo as they might not be alienated to the Clergie. Peraduenture ſome will anſwer; that Pope <hi>Clement</hi> made ſuch a law, as a temporall Prince, hauing firſt asked leaue of himſelfe, as he was Pope, to doe ſo. A very profound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration indeed, but yet not conformable to the ſolide, morall, and diuine doctrine, which teacheth that God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing giuen the gouernment of a State to him that is Prince thereof, with independent power in things temporall, he hath alſo giuen him authoritie of himſelfe, and without the licence and permiſſion of any body elſe, to make all thoſe lawes which are neceſſary to maintaine it.</p>
            <p>We neuer finde that God made any precept or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which to performe we muſt needs haue leaue of an other. In things indifferent, or good, ſo they be liberall and free, it may ſo occurre, that an error may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17247:17"/> the ſuperiors will; but for thoſe which are expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God, that which <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſayth, doth touch them neere: <hi>Obedire oportet Deo, magis quàm hominibus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> If God ſayd to a Prince, Make thoſe lawes which are neceſſarie for publike peace and tranquillitie; and if thou faileſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I will be offended with thee; and yet we muſt needs haue licence to obey him, and licence being required, whereas without, <hi>non licet:</hi> ſhall not then that which God commands be lawfull? Nature in all her finall drifts giueth alſo ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and powers as are neceſſarie for the atteining to the ſame; and ſhall God ſet downe an end and commandement which can not be executed without the fauour of men? This is too great an inconuenience. But let vs returne to the matter of the ſame law, the which as it is in it ſelfe no new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, ſo the moſt famous Ciuilians haue diſcuſſed of the ſame, and defended it for iuſt; and amongſt others, there is <hi>Baldus,</hi> the Archdeacon, the Abbat, <hi>Signarolus, Alexander,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bal. c. qua in eccleſiarum, c. eccleſia S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae de conſtit. Arch. c. R ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, de app. <hi>16.</hi> Abb. l. <hi>1.</hi> conſ. <hi>63.</hi> Signorolus conſ. <hi>21.</hi> Alex. conſ <hi>93.</hi> Barbat. l. <hi>2.</hi> conſ. <hi>14.</hi> Crotus l. <hi>1.</hi> conſ. <hi>5.</hi> Tiraq de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract conſang. §. <hi>1.</hi> gl. <hi>13.</hi> Gail l. <hi>2.</hi> conſ. <hi>32.</hi> Capit. de fac. pol. l. <hi>3.</hi> to. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Barbaccius, Crotus, Tiraquellus, Gaelius, Renatus,</hi> and <hi>Copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> by reading of whom euery one may plainly diſcouer, whether this were any ſufficient cauſe, againſt which to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with cenſures, and the principalleſt points in ſuch a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence not hauing beene duly obſerued. Whereupon it will not be altogether vnprofitable to deliuer ſome thing alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the order obſerued by the Pope herein, to the end that we may plainly ſee how many nullities paſſed in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch a buſineſſe; of ſuch a iudgment or cenſure I will not ſay, becauſe wanting all ſubſtance thereof, it can not ſo iuſtly be tearmed. The Diuines ſay, That an vniuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may well appeare externally to be a iudgment, but in it ſelfe truly it is not ſo: as alſo, That euery vniuſt iudgment is of it ſelfe nothing; and That an indirect iudgment is no more a iudgment, than a dead man is a man. But what? we ſee in it a plaine formall defect, and this of that ſubſtance, as it makes it altogether immomentall. Firſt it was declared, without any citation preceding, That the old and new lawes, of not alienating of goods, and building of Churches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17247:18"/> licence, are againſt the authoritie of the Apoſtolike See, and of Eccleſiaſticall liberty, and that the Law-makers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue herein incurred cenſure; and yet it is an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent point in all the Ciuilians, That citations are <hi>de iure natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali,</hi> and alſo very requiſit in all cauſes declaratory. The which may well ſerue for a nullitie of the aboue-mentioned <hi>Breue,</hi> and of whatſoeuer hath beene proſecuted in vertue of the ſame. But that ſo many godly men alreadie dead in Chriſt, and which haue alwayes communicated with the Popes of their times, ſhould be denounced excommunicate; what is it els, but to condemne ſo many of the Popes predeceſſors, and to auerre, that they diſcharged not ſo well their care of ſoules as they ought to haue done? And I aſſure you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them there were diuers Popes of ſingular vertue and pietie.</p>
            <p>The Pope yeelds a reaſon, why he determined to proceed againſt the Common-wealth, ſaying: <hi>Cum praetermiſſi officij noſtri, &amp; cauſae Eccleſiae deſertae à nobis rationem extremo Iudicij die exigi à Deo nullo modo velimus; neque enim exiſtimetis nos qui alioquin pacis &amp; quietis publicae cupidiſſimi ſumus, omneſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nostros cogitatus eò intendimus, vt ſoli Deo interuenientes rem Chriſtianam, quantum poſſumus, pacatè gubernemus, qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium animos, praeſertim maximorum Principum, nobiſcum ea in re conſentientes eſſe optamus, ſi aliquando Sedis Apoſtolicae autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas laedatur, ſi Eccleſiaſtca libertas, &amp; immunitas impetatur, ſi Canonum decreta negligantur, Eccleſiarum iura, &amp; Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum perſonarum priuilegia violentur, quae muneris noſtri ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt, id aliquo modo diſſimulaturos, aut officio noſtro defuturos; hac verò in re id vobis perſuaſum eſſe volumus, nos nullis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis rationibus moueri, aut quiddam praeter Dei gloriam quaerere, aliud<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habere propoſitum, niſi perfectam, quoad eius fieri poſſit, Apoſtolici regiminis functionem.</hi> And ſurely his H. not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe, may well feare a iudgement diuine, hauing offended in his Paſtorall office, becauſe God threatneth by <hi>Ieremias: Veh Paſtoribus qui diſpergunt, &amp; dilacerant gregem paſcuae meae, dicit Dominus. Ideo haec dicit Dominus Deus Iſrael
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17247:18"/> ad paſtores qui paſcunt populum meum, diſperſiſtis gregem meum, &amp; eieciſtis eos, &amp; non viſitaſtis eos: Ecce ego viſitabo ſuper vos malitiam ſtudiorum veſtrorum, ait Dominus.</hi> And to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he promiſeth: <hi>Dabo vobis Paſtores iuxta cor meum, &amp; paſcent vos ſcientia &amp; doctrina.</hi> For this is moſt certeine, that the very ſumme of all Paſtoral charge conſiſteth in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, in holy admonitions and inſtruction to Chriſtian conuerſation, in the adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, a care ouer the poore, and in the puniſhment of ſuch offences as abſolutely exclude vs out of the Kingdome of God: theſe being things which our Sauior Chriſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended ouer vnto <hi>S. Peter,</hi> committing them to his charge; the which things only were practiſed by him, as alſo by the holy Martyrs his ſucceſſots, and the holy Confeſſors alſo, which ſucceeded them from time to time; but not in ſuch a maner, as the darkneſſe ſucceeds the light.</p>
            <p>In the ſacred Scriptures wee learne, that the glorie of God conſiſteth in the propagation of the Goſpell, and in good Chriſtian life;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> and in briefe (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaks) in the mortification of the externall man, in the life of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and in the exerciſe of charitable deeds. For if the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God ſhould lie in the abundance of Temporall goods, we might haue iuſt cauſe to be afrayd of our ſelues, ſeeing Chriſt hath promiſed to his nothing but pouertie,<note place="margin">Iohn 15.</note> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, diſcommodities, and to conclude (as the ſame vulgar know very well) troubles and want are the true trials of the ftiends of God;<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> and no man (ſayth the Goſpell) followes Chriſt, but after he hath taken vpon his ſhoulders his owne croſſe.</p>
            <p>That which by ſome one hath beene diſperſed in diuers places, and to many perſons, is very different from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>S. Paul;</hi> which is,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> That it can not be ſeene wherein this city can be ſo truly commended for religion; for though almes and charitable deeds towards the poore abound in the ſame, as alſo ornaments of the Church, and worſhip diuine; yet for all this, the very ſubſtance of a Chriſtian conſiſteth in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17247:19"/> fauouring the Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction: and in <hi>Venice</hi> we ſee the contrarie to this.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> The ſaying of <hi>S. Paul</hi> is: <hi>Si tradidero corpus meum, ita vt ardeam, charitatem autem non habuero nihil ſum.</hi> We reade in the holy Euangeliſts, that our Sauiour in the day of iudgment will demand an account of the wicked for not hauing vſed the works of mercy &amp; pitie: <hi>Eſuriui enim, &amp; non dediſtis mihi manducare:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Sitiui, &amp; non dediſtis mihi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: Hoſpes eram, &amp; non collegiſtis me: Nudus, &amp; non operui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis me: Infirmus, &amp; in carcere, &amp; non viſitaſtis me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſo we need not to feare, that God will call vs to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for cutting off all libertie from the wicked to offend their neighbour; or that a part or portion of goods belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, ſhould be allotted to the Seculars: nay more than that, we may boldly giue all the goods of the Church to the poore, without any wayes offending of God therein.</p>
            <p>Neither may we heere alſo omit to ponder a little the laſt words of that <hi>Breue,</hi> where it thus runneth: <hi>Quinimo, nulla alia ratione meliùs publica illa Chriſtianae religionis incommoda, in quibus euitandis tantopere inſiſtitis, longe à vobis propulſabitis, quàm ſi Eccleſiarum, &amp; Eccleſiaſticorum, qui pro vobis dies ac noctes excubant, &amp; aſſiduas ad Deum preces effundunt, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitates &amp; iura (prout religioſos &amp; pios viros decet) conſeruaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Common-wealth queſtionleſſe hath need to be aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the Clergies prayers, for which cauſe ſhe dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendeth herſelfe vnto them, as vnderſtanding well what the Wiſe man ſayth:<note place="margin">Eccle. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Deprecatio pauperis ex ore vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad aures perueniet.</hi> And they grieue, when as but few intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe holy actions, by their euill example, they are an occaſion of great tranſgreſſion in the Laitie: whereupon in ſtead of pacifying diuine Iuſtice, and mouing him to mercie towards vs, they rather ſtirre vp the more Gods wrath to puniſh vs, by the meanes of Infidels and miſcreants. And we muſt not beleeue that the prayers of the fortunate and rich are apteſt to appeaſe his Maieſtie diuine, of whom it is written:<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Non deſpexit deprecationem pauperis:</hi> conſidering
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17247:19"/> that then a number of Monks and Hermits, which did and do liue in great pouertie and humilitie, had done and do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie euill therein, they being otherwiſe of a firme beliefe, that in ſuch a State their prayers will more eaſily aſcend before the preſence of God.</p>
            <p>But now it is high time to paſſe ouer vnto the third point in controuerſie; the which conſiſts in the matter of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing Eccleſiaſticks, the which ſubiect muſt diſtinctly be entreated of, ſeeing the <hi>Breue</hi> vpon this argument was alſo preſented at an other time. Peraduenture diuine Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence heerein had a hand, that an error ſhould be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by one of the Popes miniſters, whoſoeuer it were, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of the <hi>Breues,</hi> to the end his holineſſe might haue ſome time better to weigh of what moment the affaire was, which he then tooke in hand; but notwithſtanding this, his Ho. forbare not expreſly to command, that the other <hi>Breue</hi> vpon the two priſoners ſhould be preſented, as it was on the 25 of Februarie, with this ſuperſcription; <hi>Marino Grimano Duci, &amp; Reipublicae Venetoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> although his Ho. was priuie to the death of that Prince, which had fallen out two moneths before, and he had procured congratulatorie offices to paſſe betwixt him &amp; this renowmed preſent Prince his ſucceſſor. Some Canoniſt peraduenture may defend this action with their doctrine; <hi>Papa eſt iudex viuorum, &amp; mortuorum;</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may ſuppoſe he imagined thus, that the ſelfe ſame dignitie remaining, the change of perſons was of no great importance; in which point notwithſtanding, the Canoniſts are quite oppoſite againſt him, who are of opinion, that in treating of cenſures, it being tearmed an odious ſubiect, the words ought moſt ſtrictly to be conſtrued: ſo that if he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this preſent renowmed to be ſufficiently admoniſhed thereby, they will no waies grant it him; for euen in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he hath proceeded againſt him, without obſeruing a circumſtance very material in iudgments, which is, a cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the declaration, and an admonition for the cenſure. We muſt hold this for infallible, that if the Pope had but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17247:20"/> duly regarded the reaſons whereupon the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> groundeth her authoritie for iudging perſons Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, he would neuer haue mooued one word about the ſame; but ſeeing he would not diſcuſſe nor heare the reaſons of the ſame Common-wealth, with that patience, maturitie, and charitie, as was expected from his Ho. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the generall Father of all Chriſtendome: no maruell though he blame the iudgements of the Common-wealth, affirming them to be grounded vpon vſe and naked cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and vpon ſome Pontificall <hi>Breue.</hi> The Senate made anſwer to the Popes <hi>Breues</hi> in few words, and that they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred how new cauſe of controuerſie daily grew, and he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to ſhake thoſe foundations vpon which their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had beene grounded, for the ſpace of a thouſand two hundred yeeres. For euen from the cradle and ſwathing clouts of the Common-wealth, their predeceſſors receiued authoritie from God, to puniſh any kind of delinquents, the which they haue continually put in practiſe to the honor of his diuine Maieſtie, with publike peace, the approbation of his H. precedents, and vniuerſall commendation and praiſe. Of cuſtome there was no mention made, conſidering that their power was much more firmly and deeply rooted, then vpon an vſe, though neuer ſo immemorable, becauſe they held this doctrine of the beſt Diuines and Canoniſts for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, that the exemption of perſons Eccleſiaſticall from the Secular Courts, vpon offences not Eccleſiaſticall but Temporall, or as <hi>Iustinian</hi> ſaith, ciuill, comes not <hi>De iure diuino,</hi> but through the priuiledges of Princes; except one ſhould be ſo madde as to take the ſignification of theſe words, <hi>ius diuinum</hi> ſo largely, or abuſiuely, as to extend them to <hi>ius humanum</hi> too.</p>
            <p>This doctrine, that if the Clergie were not by ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or priuiledge exempted, they were to be ſubiect to the Secular Magiſtrate, it is declared and confirmed by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the old Teſtament, where we may ſee, that all Kings haue commanded, iudged, and puniſhed Prieſts; and that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17247:20"/> this was not performed by wicked and reaſonable good Kings onely, but by thoſe alſo moſt holy and godly, <hi>Dauid, Salomon, Ioas, Ezechia,</hi> and <hi>Ioſia;</hi> and in the Goſpell we finde it preciſely in the words which our Sauiour Chriſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto <hi>Pilate, Non haberes poteſtatem aduerſus me vllam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.</note> 
               <hi>niſi tibi datum eſſet de ſuper;</hi> vnto which we may adde that (if one would but make an extrauagant conſtruction thereof) the expoſition of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> S <hi>Bernard,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gaietano</hi> is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Super Ioh. tract.</hi> 116. <hi>Epist.</hi> 42. <hi>in</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 62. <hi>a.</hi> 1. Act. 25.</note> that <hi>Pilats</hi> iudgement was indeed very wicked, but not vſurped; and beſides this, we haue a confirmation alſo thereof in the example of S. <hi>Paul;</hi> who doubting leſt that <hi>Festus</hi> vnder pretext of iudging him at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> would haue deliuered him into the Iewes hands, he appealed to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> which he would neuer haue done, if he had not beene his lawfull Iudge, it being a mortall ſinne to appeale to him, that hath no lawfull power nor authoritie to be ſo appealed vnto. A moderne writer makes a profound conſideration heereof; which is, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> would haue appealed to <hi>Peter,</hi> but he did not, becauſe it would haue beene reputed in him a great follie; a conſideration ſurely worthie of a perſpicuous and deepe vnderſtanding, but yet not beſeeming the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute conſtancie of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that he did forbeare to ſpeake a trueth for feare of being thought a foole: He had not this reſpect before <hi>Festus,</hi> and he ceaſed not to vtter thoſe words vpon which the Prefect anſwered him; <hi>Inſanis Paule:</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe then ſaid;<note place="margin">Act. 26. 1. Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Nos praedicamus Ieſum Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixum, Hebrais quidem ſcandalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gentibus autem ſtultitiam;</hi> and yet for all this, he deſiſted not to ſpeake and preach that which he knew to be reputed follie: let not this therefore in any wiſe be iniurious to S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſeeing doubtleſſe that moſt holy &amp; exemplar Apoſtle neuer deſerued it. And what can we ſay to the precepts of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; the ſame S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> which are <hi>Subiecti igitur eſtote omni humanae creaturae propter Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſiue Regi quaſi praecellenti, ſiue Ducibus tamquam ab eo miſſis ad vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam malefactorum, laudem verò bonorum, quia ſic eſt voluntas Dei?</hi> and of this, <hi>admonet illos Principibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ad Tit. 3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Poteſtatibus
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17247:21"/> ſubditos eſſe dicto obedire?</hi> as alſo that which we finde written in the 13. chap. to the <hi>Romans,</hi> which may ſerue euen for a Sunne, to diſſipate the clouds, of whatſoeuer error or doubt: <hi>Omnis anima poteſtatibus ſublimioribus ſubdita ſit: non eſt enim poteſtas niſi à Deo quae autem ſunt, à Deo ordinatae ſunt: ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> qui reſiſtit poteſtati, Dei ordinationi reſiſtit; qui autem reſiſtunt, ipſi ſibi damnationem acquirunt: nam principes non ſunt timori boni operis, ſed mali. Vis autem non timere poteſtatem, bonum fac, &amp; habebis laudem ex illa, Dein. Miniſter eſt tibi in bonum: ſi autem malum feceris, time, non enim ſine cauſa gladium portat, Dei enim Miniſter eſt, vindex in iram ei, qui malum agit; ideo neceſſitate ſubditi estote, non ſolùm propter iram, ſed etiam propter conſcientiam: Ideo enim &amp; tributa praeſtatis, miniſtri enim Dei ſunt, in hoc ipſum ſeruientes: Reddite ergo omnibus debita, cui tributum, tributum, cui vectigal, vectigal, cui timorem, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Expoſ. ad Rom. num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>72</hi> ſuper Epiſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m ad Rom. Hom..... in expoſ.</note> 
               <hi>cui honorem, honorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke in S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for he putteth himſelf alſo now into the number of thoſe which are ſubiect to the ſecular Prince; obſerue <hi>Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Theophylact,</hi> and <hi>Oecmenius,</hi> who with very manifeſt and plaine words include within this compaſſe, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Prieſts, and Monks. Read S. <hi>Thomas</hi> vpon the ſame place, and you ſhall ſee how he moſt cleerely affirmeth, that all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall exemption grew from Princes their priuiledges.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ep.</hi> 42.</note> But S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> yet ſomewhat more perſpicuouſly affirmeth the ſame, writing thus to an Archbiſhop; <hi>Omnis anima pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatibus ſublimioribus ſubdita eſt, ſi omnis, eſt &amp; veſtra: quis vos excipit ab vniuerſitate? ſi quis tentat excipere, conatur decipere.</hi> Let theſe Opponents but well conſider, whether euer any of the ancient holy Popes, Biſhops, or other Prieſts affirmed, that they were exempted from the authoritie of Princes and Magiſtrates; and I know they ſhall not finde one: but ſo they may well finde that euery one hath confeſſed this ſubiection, denying onely the iuſtice of the cauſe for which they were condemned.</p>
            <p>We haue a famous example of this in <hi>Polycarpus</hi> Biſhop
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17247:21"/> of <hi>Smirna,</hi> and diſciple to <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, one of the excellent Founders of our faith; whoſe words reported by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> are theſe: <hi>Magiſtratibus enim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſeb.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; poteſtatibus à Deo conſtitutis eum honorem, qui noſtrorum animorum ſaluti noſtrae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Religioni nihil affert detrimenti, pro dignitate tribuere docemur.</hi> Some ſay, that the Apoſtles were enioyned obedience vnto Princes while they were Heathens, but not after they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtians; and this was, by reaſon that the Clergie in reſpect of their holy Order, and the ſpirituall authoritie that they retaine, are greater. But theſe men <hi>S. Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> anſwereth in a few words: <hi>Si enim Paulus cum Gentiles adhuc eſſent Principes, praecepit, multo magis oportet &amp; fidelibus exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, quod ſi maiora tibi concredita eſſe dixeris, diſce non nunc ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris tui tempus eſſe, peregrinus enim hic es, &amp; aduena, tempus erit cum omnibus apparebis illuſtrior, nunc vero vita tua abſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita eſt cum Chriſto, in Deo; quando Chriſtus comparuerit, tunc &amp; vos comparebitis in gloria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is it that may well doubt, but that Eccleſiaſticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions haue beene the priuiledges of Princes, when the ſelfe ſame lawes and priuiledges are extant? and we ſee they were not granted all at one time, but by little and little; the which I will ſet downe according to their times, becauſe it greatly importeth for any mans ſatisfaction, that deſires hereof to be certified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, about the yeere 1315,<note place="margin">C. Theod. de epiſ. &amp; cler. l. <hi>2.</hi> ibid. l. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> exempted the Clergie from publike, perſonall, and Court ſeruices; <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Conſtante</hi> his ſonnes added heereunto an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from all illiberall and ſordid actions, as alſo from impoſitions; and they priuiledged Biſhops onely from the arreſts of Secular Courts,<note place="margin">ibid. l. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> all others of the Clergie ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnder the Secular Iudge, aſwell in caſes criminall as ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil: and about this there afterwards were enacted two lawes, one by <hi>Valente</hi> and <hi>Gratianus</hi> about the yeere 380,<note place="margin">ibid. l. <hi>23.</hi> ibid. l. <hi>37.</hi> ibid. l. <hi>41.</hi> ibid. l. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> in the 400; but then much about the yeere 420, <hi>Honorius,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the ſecond, and after that the ſame <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> with <hi>Valentinian</hi> the third,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17247:22"/> put ouer the triall of the Clergie to the Biſhops, ſo both parts are well content, and if one of them would not accept of the Biſhop,<note place="margin">C. de epiſc. &amp; clo. l. cum cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici, C. eod. l. omnis qui.</note> referring them then ouer to the Secular Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: the which was alſo confirmed by <hi>Martian</hi> in 460, and by <hi>Leo</hi> his ſucceſſour: finally, by <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> about the yeere 560: all difference and varietie was remooued and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp by a law of this import,<note place="margin">Nouell. <hi>83.</hi> Nouell...</note> That the Clergie in ciuill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould be ſubiect to the Biſhop, and in criminall to the Secular Iudge; the which continued in force til 630. When <hi>Heraclius</hi> further exempted them from the Secular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, as well in caſes criminall as ciuill, yet euer reſerued en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire the Princes immediate Deputies and Subſtitutes. And thus it was obſerued while the diuiſion of the Empire; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo after the ſame maner and faſhion the Greeke Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued as long as that Empire laſted.</p>
            <p>But indeed in the Weſt the French Emperours and Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the Kings of <hi>Italie,</hi> they haue diuerſly obſerued herein; ſometimes committing of iudgements to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and otherwhiles ſentencing not only Prieſts and Biſhops, but euen the Popes themſelues; one while referring them in part to be iudged by the Spiritualtie, and in part by the Magiſtrates, according as the alteration of times permitted; at one time the Popes authoritie preuailing, and at another the Emperours. And at laſt, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond, about 1220, made an authenticall inſertion into <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex,</hi> That no man might bring any ciuill or criminall Clergy man before any Secular Iudge; and whoſoeuer readeth the titles <hi>Epiſcopis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auth. C. de epiſc. &amp; cler. l. ſtatuimus.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Clericis, &amp; de Epiſcopali audientia, vel de Epiſcopali iudicio,</hi> in <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> his <hi>Codex,</hi> he may finde all theſe lawes, and be fully informed, how Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall exemption hath beene a benignitie and fauour vouchſafed by the Emperours; as alſo they ſhall be certified, that though they granted exemption to the Clergie from the power of their Magiſtrates, yet did they neuer except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from their owne higheſt and ſupreame power. The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of puniſhing whoſoeuer offendeth againſt the lawes, is ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17247:22"/> annexed to all principallitie, as it is indiuiduall from the ſame: and to ſay that a Prince hath one in his State not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to him in cauſes temporall or any other concerning publike good, it implieth ſo much, as if he were not a Prince. A naturall bodie could not comport, that there ſhould be in it any one member not allotted to the ſeruice of the whole and entire; much leſſe can a ciuill bodie endure, that there ſhould be a man in the middeſt of it, that did acknowledge any other but the Prince, in humane and temporall things. The Pope himſelfe, in things ſpirituall, exempts whom he liſts, from Biſhops and Archbiſhops, but from himſelfe, he can priuiledge none, without deſiſting to be Pope. The Venetian Common-wealth being freely begun, and borne as it were, about the yeere 420, notwithſtanding (as it vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally falles out in all great States) not ſo expatiated in her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning into ſo large and ſpacious dominion, yet hath it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from God no leſſe than other great Princes in their mightie Empires, authoritie and power ouer any perſon, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing within her dominions; and the ſame Common-wealth hath ſuffered the Clergie to enioy the ſame priuiledge from Magiſtrates, as they were granted from time to time in the townes and cities of the Empire; being contented to puniſh in them thoſe exorbitances, which being vile and enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, might be a diſturbance to publike peace and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and there remaine Records of Eccleſiaſticks puniſhed for all ſorts of offences, and ſometimes for ſuch as would now be counted but ſlight, but yet in reſpect of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular circumſtance, deſeruing worthily to be puniſhed by the Common-wealth. And though the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince the yeere 1160,<note place="margin">C. at ſi clerici de iudi. C. clerici eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. C. cum non ab homine eod. C. qualiter &amp; quando eod.</note> haue made diuers decrees for the priuiledge of Clergie men, yet haue theſe beene receiued ſo abſolutely in no place, by any Prince, neither beene able to effect, but that offences of high treaſon haue beene alwayes ſubiect to Secular iudgement. Thorowout all <hi>Italie</hi> they puniſh Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons (without any warning) which goe not in their habits, notwhithſtanding any exemptions or decrees
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17247:23"/> Pontificall. In <hi>Spaine</hi> they do the like, vpon the wearing of armes, and diuers other offences. In <hi>France</hi> they diſtinguiſh betweene common and priuiledged offences, and only the former are referred to the Clergie, and the latter to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Iudge.</p>
            <p>And ſo in like maner, this Common-wealth hath diuided offences into thoſe grieuous, and others light and little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting: thoſe of no moment are put ouer to the Church, and thoſe grieuous, committed to the Magiſtrates. And thus haue they alwayes proceeded in executing the iuſtice and libertie of their iuriſdiction. I will not affirme, that this is only a cuſtome, which being contrarie to a law, hath in tract of time worne out the vigor of the ſame law it ſelfe: for we doubt not, but that cuſtome muſt not preuaile againſt the law of God and of Nature, though it had continued for many thouſand yeeres; and we will readily confeſſe thus much, That if God himſelfe had euer excepted perſons Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, the act of any Prince whatſoeuer, decreed to the contrarie, would be but an vſurpation and offence againſt God. And further, to the former we will annex this alſo (by their fauours which ſay, That their priuiledge growes <hi>de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re diuino</hi>) That if it were ſo, the Pope could haue no power to bring them vnder, becauſe Seculars ſhould not then be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to put in practiſe that, by the Popes diſpenſation, which God had prohibited. God hath forbidden Secular men to ſay Maſſe, to confeſſe, and ſuch like: the Pope can not by any of his diſpenſations beare them out herein. And if they tell me, that this is <hi>ius diuinum,</hi> indiſpenſable, but the Popes is diſpenſable, not to argue or labour to ſhew the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which is in ſaying <hi>ius diuinum,</hi> and yet diſpenſable by humane authoritie,<note place="margin">Innoc. c. cum Apoſtolica. de ſim. de priuil. c. quod quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam de verb. ſignif. c. in bis. c. ſuper qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam.</note> it may ſuffice to anſwer them: that all the meanes which may be obtained by a Diſpenſation from the Pope, may alſo be acquired by a cuſtome, which may grow and propagate contrarie to a law: and if we ſhould ſuppoſe the execution of Clearks to haue beene firſt ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by law, and alſo executed, and that afterwards through
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17247:23"/> immemorable vſe and cuſtome, the contrary were preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; I ſay, it might lawfully be practiſed and put in vſe. But in this our caſe, the vſe and cuſtome of the Common-wealth preceedeth any law which priuiledgeth eccleſiaſtical perſons from Secular triall in enormious criminall cauſes, and no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree whatſoeuer, which the Church hath made, can preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice them a whit. To which may be added, the ſecret ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation heereof in all the Popes, who ſeeing and knowing thus much; if they had not iudged it conuenient, they would haue reprehended it; and moreouer the expreſſe approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions themſelues of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eight; <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixt; and <hi>Paulus</hi> the Third; whoſe <hi>Breues</hi> are reſerued in the ſecret rolles of Common-wealth, doe truely maintaine what ſhe hath iuſtly conſtituted. The which <hi>Innocentius</hi> euidently declareth in his <hi>Breue,</hi> directed to the Patriarke of <hi>Venice,</hi> deliuered on the laſt of October 1487, in which intimating with what good reaſon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth did ſentence Clergie men, not onely in thoſe moſt horrible, but alſo in all other offences that were anie waies odious and vile, he vſeth theſe words; <hi>Nos attendentes priuilegia ad bene viuendum dari non ad delinquendum, illa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeſidio bonis contra improbos eſſe debere, non autem malis ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum facultatem, &amp;c.</hi> A matter which does not onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fall out in theſe our daies, but then alſo it was moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and vſuall, as Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth in his <hi>Breue</hi> to the Patriarch of <hi>Venice,</hi> deliuered the 2. of Iune 1474 teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in theſe words; <hi>Cogimur non ſine cordis noſtri dolore, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima quae nollemus de perſonis Eccleſiaſticis audire ex iſta Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, praeſertim in qua ſaepè nonnulli aut monetas adulteraſſe, aut crimen loeſae maiestatis admiſiſſe dicuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any man to prooue that priuiledges are <hi>de iure diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> ſhould alledge the example of <hi>Constantine</hi> in the Councel of <hi>Nice;</hi> let him but reade it ouer againe well, and then tell me whether it make for or againſt his intention. <hi>Iuſtiman</hi> the Emperor his Nouels: the 3. 5. 6. 11. 123. 131. 133. 137. with abundant perſpicuitie ſet downe, what exemptions were
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17247:24"/> proper to Clergie men vnder that Emperour, and what they enioied before his time. If then in the beginning by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Emperours, and afterwards through ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuencie they haue obtained priuiledge; why ſhould they ſo ſet vp their briſtles when the Venecian Common-wealth ſaies: that though others in their State haue permitted that enormious crimes alſo in the Clergie, ſhould be iudged by the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, ſuppoſing and thinking that this might ſtand well with their gouernment; yet they neuer yeelded nor conſented thereunto, as reputing it a thing contrarie to their publike peace and tranquillitie.</p>
            <p>We might heere further alledge; that theſe exemptions are not grounded alike in no Dominion nor Kingdome; and he that does but read what the Cryminaliſts haue written, but eſpecially <hi>Clarius</hi> in particular,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. § <hi>fin. q.</hi> 36.</note> ſhall cleerely ſee how diuerſly in diuers places theſe priuiledges haue beene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and practiſed; this being an indiſſoluble argument, that they are not <hi>de iure diuino:</hi> ſo as cuſtome may ouerrule them, and that the Popes decrees vpon this point, haue not in all places beene receiued.</p>
            <p>And heere it were alſo good to conſider, that in the <hi>Breue</hi> of the 10. of December, this preſent Pope ſaith; a Canon and an Abbat are impriſoned: <hi>Perſonas in Eccleſiaſtica dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate, conſtitutas.</hi> There might a thouſand Papall <hi>Breues</hi> be produced to ſhew, that <hi>Cannonicatus non est dignitas:</hi> but at laſt ſpying this error in their Printed Monitorie, they haue excluded the Canon, and mentioned onely the Abbat, <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perſonam, in dignitate Eccleſiaſtica conſtitutam;</hi> ſo that by this we may collect, that euen in the Popes <hi>Breues</hi> there may alſo be errors, eſpecially when they are wrtiten with too much haſte, which is an occaſion they are not therein ſo conſiderate as reaſon requires. And yet there is ſome doubt whether theſe commendatorie Abbatſhips be dignities or no, in that the ſacred Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> prohibiteth all <hi>Commendams:</hi> yet it greatly concernes this Treatiſe which we haue in hand, that it ſhould be a dignitie, and that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17247:24"/> the Pope may laie his foundation ſo as if it were a poore Prieſt vnbeneficed, the matter would not be ſo great. For the qualitie of the place is a ſpeciall matter to make the priuiledge greater and more authenticall; conſidering it is moſt certaine, that there are orders appointed in the Church (ſuch as the Sacraments are) <hi>iure diuino,</hi> amongſt which Prieſthood is the higheſt: but for theſe dignities of Abbats, Priors, Archdeacons, they haue beene brought in <hi>iure humano:</hi> wherefore if exemption and priuiledge were <hi>ex iure diuino,</hi> it would belong principally to the Prieſts, though they had no title at all; and not to certaine ſpecial &amp; remarquable places, as they would haue it. And out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion he that goes about to diſſolue this firme knot of equity &amp; reaſon, he cannot attempt it without pain and great labor. This argument requires the conſideration of two qualities in the perſon of the Pope; the one of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> a Biſhop of that particular Church, and the vniuerſall head ouer all others; and an other, as he is Prince of that State, which he poſſeſſeth; for though at this preſent they are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, yet is it not neceſſarie that either the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Prince of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be a Pope; as that the Pope ſhould be a Prince. It boots not now to expreſſe when both theſe qualities were vnited, for it is peraduenture aboue foure hundred yeeres: and yet ſay it had ſo beene this eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres, this would not a whit diſable our diſcourſe; as Pope in the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> he hath there his Vicar or Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, and in other cities vnder him, Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall Rectors; and as a Prince he hath Miniſters, Gouernors, Iudges, and others, who though they be partly Prieſts, yet as being Prieſts they doe not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcharge thoſe offices, and many of them alſo are meere Lay men. Now when any Eccleſiaſticall Prieſt or Friar, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any enormious offence, we ſee, that the Biſhops or thoſe that diſcharge Eccleſiaſticall places, doe not puniſh them,<note place="margin">Three ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all priſons ſo called.</note> but rather Gouernors, Auditors, and ſuch like. How often haue we ſeene <hi>Terre de noua, Corte Sauella,</hi> and the towne of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17247:25"/> 
               <hi>Boloqua</hi> with other Lay priſons, full of Prieſts and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Friars; and that which importeth more then all the reſt, during the Popedomes of <hi>Sixtus</hi> and <hi>Clement,</hi> there were Friars hanged, with their regular habite on their backs. This aſſuredly was but iuſt and neceſſarie, for otherwiſe the State Eccleſiaſticall could not liue in peace. Wherefore other States are not free from this neceſſitie; and if his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe would pleaſe to meaſure other mens occaſions by his owne, he would not condemne Princes for puniſhing ſuch Prieſts, as liue not like Prieſts.</p>
            <p>And we muſt not ſuppoſe that in other States there is that perfection which is not in our owne; but rather we ought to giue an example of that in our ſelues which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire others ſhould be; for ſeeing the euil which ariſeth of the contrarie, wee ſhall ſeeme to haue a feeling of others neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
            <p>I know well what anſwer will be made, and that is this; that the Pope hath concurring with him the two dignities before mentioned; the one of a Prince, and the other of chiefe Biſhop; and therefore as a Prince, ſeeing it neceſſarie for the good gouernment of his State, that the enormious tranſgreſſions of the Clergie, ſhould be puniſhed by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular power; he demandeth leaue of himſelfe as being high Prieſt, and as he grants it vnto himſelfe; ſo he can likewiſe affoord it vnto others, if they requeſt it by way of fauor; this is a medicine more inſupportable then the diſeaſe, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the body more; &amp; an anſwer which diuideth alſo things inuiſible. Would it not be a more likely thing to affirme; that the Pope as he is a Prince, knowes how neceſſary it is for the good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſake of a State, to puniſh with tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral authority euerie one which diſturbeth the peace, though he be one of the Church; but he not being able to diſcerne the occaſions of other Princes and States, nor conſenting to the authoritie which they haue from God, he only takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his owne proper authority, as he is a Pope, for which cauſe he would alſo haue an hand in there gouernments.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17247:25"/>
            <p>Heere ſome obiect, ſaying; all puniſhment is for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of a malefactor; otherwiſe, if it haue not reference to ſo good an end, it may rather be tearmed a tyrannicall act: and the correction of euery offender pertaines to his ſuperior. Wherefore it toucheth not a Prince greatly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an eccleſiaſticall delinquent be puniſhed or no; let him in Gods name looke to the puniſhment of the Laietie; for if Clergie men be not chaſtiſed, the Prelats muſt giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof vnto God. And ſurely this reaſon ſhould haue concluded very well, if the <hi>maior</hi> thereof had beene true, which is, that the puniſhment of a malefactor was the onely end of criminall iuſtice. It is an end indeed, but a ſecondary end, and the leaſt of two, it being for a priuate benefit; but the principall is a publike end, and conſiſteth in two things; one, in maintaining of good cuſtomes and conuerſation in the Citizens, and in the citie tranquillitie and peace; and an other is, that when any one vſurpeth ouer his neighbour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage or hard dealing, by afflicting and preiudicing of him againſt reaſon, by inflicting a proportionable puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againe vpon the other, to reduce things to an equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. When the Eccleſiaſticall perſon, laying aſide the feare of God and of the world, doth violate the lawes, he giues therein a publike offence, by being an euill example vnto the Lay man, who by ſuch an imitation grow bad and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and moreouer he inſtigates him whom he iniured, to ſeeke reuenge, with the ſubuerſion of publike quiet and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. It ought therefore to be a Princes ſpeciall care, that offences may be puniſhed; otherwiſe, by the reaſon aboue alledged, a Prince might neuer puniſh a ſtranger which ſhould offend in his State, ſeeing he being none of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect he need not be carefull of his profit or good. A Prince doth puniſh a ſtranger, not as hauing in this a ſimple refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to correction, but to defend his owne ſubiect from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, as he is bound, and to cut off all wicked example which might induce cuſtomes pernicious to publike peace. And therefore it preuailes not to ſay, If it be neceſſarie for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17247:26"/> publike good, that a Clergie man be puniſhed, let the Prince procure him puniſhment from his Prelate, and ſo let him ſuffer the Lay Magiſtrate to execute the ſame.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which, we muſt obſerue, that the Church, according to the ſacred Canons, cannot puniſh in <hi>poena ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis,</hi> no not for the moſt grieuous and enormous offences that are committed; but the chaſticements of the Church muſt be with cenſures of ſuſpenſion, priuation, depoſition, or penalties of degradations; or els they impoſe the profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able penance of prayer, faſting, and other charitable deeds; and the ſeuereſt ſentence which they denounce, is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine one within a Monaſterie, or ſome ſtrait priſon, there to performe perpetuall penance: of which notwithſtanding, we haue not beene eie-witneſſes in theſe our daies, vpon any offence, how hainous ſoeuer committed. And if ſome whiles they enioyne this penance for any long time; after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation made of the penitents humilitie, and his willing obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, they quickly forgiue him, and readily receiue him to grace and fauour. And notwithſtanding that it was <hi>Iuſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> owne commandement, that offenders ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Secular power; yet the common and receiued opinion of all Canoniſts is, that it is only to be performed in three caſes; that is, in the caſe of hereſie, of falſifying letters Apoſtolicall, and vpon conſpiracie againſt their owne Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: for they reſt, they affirmatiuely hold, That if a Clerke had committed neuer ſo foule or hainous an offence, yea, though he had killed the Pope himſelfe, if he did but offer to vndergo due penance for the ſame, that he ought not to be degraded, nor deliuered ouer to the Secular Iudge, but to be confined to perpetuall priſon.</p>
            <p>From this qualitie and forme of iuſtice it followeth, that Clergie men would readily tranſgreſſe the lawes; for they feeling more profit and pleaſure in their offence, than loſſe or paine in the puniſhment, they make choiſe rather of this chaſtiſement, it being of them more lightly eſteemed, than to be depriued of their proper luſts and appetites: and ſo,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17247:26"/> being in no feare at all of their liues, (a thing, that for the moſt part doth moſt bridle and terrifie all malefactors) and hoping, though ſome Eccleſiaſtical penalties be impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, to take vp the matter againe quickly, they make it lawfull without any law at all, to enter into any flagition: as alſo Eccleſiaſticall Courts puniſh not thoſe offences moſt which diſturbe publike tranquillitie, but rather thoſe which abridge and infringe their owne intereſts. For the falſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of letters Apoſtolicall, or a conſpiracie againſt a Biſhop, which are the caſes (as was aboue ſaid) for which degradation was inſtituted; theſe touch not the Laity ſo neere: but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, high rreaſon, falſification of coine, man-ſlaughter, for which they would impoſe their Eccleſiaſticall penance; theſe are the enormities which for the ſeruice of publike qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and peace ſhould be puniſhed with rare and exemplar ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie. And certeinly a Prelate which gouernes his Clerks, can not well do any act, but that which will haue moſt refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to themſelues only, &amp; their owne benefit: neither can he reſpect the profit of the whole common wealth in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his prieſts, euen as an houſholder doth puniſh his ſons &amp; ſeruants, but with a reſpect to the good of his owne houſe only. The executions and chaſtiſements of Princes only, and their Subſtitutes are directed, and truly tend to common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, which is his reall and true end. To ſay that a Clerke ſhould be puniſhed by his Prelate for hainous offences, which breake publike peace, it is no other, but to ſay, Let that puniſhment haue reference to the good of Eccleſiaſticall Order; and for the Laitie, let them participate only of the preiudice which groweth from ſuch offences as the other commit; and of the good which ſhould ariſe from their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, let them haue no part at all. And to ſpeake bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the trueth; Prelates neuer puniſh Prieſts for offences committed againſt Secular men, but vpon great inſtance made vnto them by the Magiſtrate, or for feare leſt they ſhould ſupplie the others default. And not without ſome reaſon: for their care is how to gouerne the Presbyterie, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17247:27"/> not how to defend the Secular. But a Prince that receiues tribute and other ſeruices from his ſubiects, in defence of their liues, honour, or goods, he can not without ſinning abandon them, when they are oppreſſed by their inſolencie, who vnder colour of priuilege runne into all impieties, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that malefactours ſhould ſcape vnpuniſhed; or els to be chaſtiſed only with Spirituall penance: but the Prince is bound to puniſh them for preſeruation of iuſtice, and the example of others; eſpecially the ſame Prince being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the almightie Creator, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Miniſter Dei Vindex in iram ei qui malum agit:</hi> wherein if he faile, he is alſo puniſhed with depriuation of his State: <hi>Regnum de gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in gentem transfertur, propter iniuſtitias, iniurias, contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias, &amp; diuerſos dolos.</hi> And beſides the offence vnto God, whereinto a Prince runnes by abandoning his ſubiects, and they wanting their due protection, other euils hereof enſue; all which do tend vnto publike ruine. Secular men thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Prieſts in their liues, honor, or goods, &amp; ſeeing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues depriued of that iuſt reuenge which publike authority performeth herein, they are with ſome colour of reaſon inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as it were heereby to priuate proſecutions; and which is worſe, fearing multiplication of wrongs, nor hoping for iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice at the Prelats hand, they go about to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it with their own; and thus of one growes a thouſand other inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which procure ſedition &amp; grieuous diſturbances in cities.</p>
            <p>And for that which is further vrged in defence of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall iudgements, That exemption from Lay Courts is granted to Clerks in honour of that Order, which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to diuine worſhip, it is but reaſon it ſhould be reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. This is a thing which euery good iudgment will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret quite contrarie: for if it be ſayd in reſpect of him who hath committed the offence; firſt, he deſerues not to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored; and <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth: <hi>Vis non timere poteſtatem, bonum fac, &amp; habebis laudem.</hi> For <hi>Socrates</hi> ſayd very well: Vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie he is that ſinneth, but yet much more vnhappie if he ſhun puniſhment. And it can much leſſe be auerred in honour of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17247:27"/> the good, for they may be blemiſhed by the companie of the wicked; and good men are moſt honoured, when they are without wicked companie. <hi>S. Paul</hi> aduiſed vs: <hi>Auferte malum de vobiſmetipſis, modicum fermenti totam maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpit:</hi> ſo that if they, according to the rule of the ſacred canons, by taking away of a wicked mans life, cannot exclude them out of their number, it will ſtand well with Ecleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dignitie, that their goodneſſe being ſeparated from the wicked by the authoritie of the Prince, it may remaine by this meanes the more pure and ſincere, and therefore the more honoured. And we can not ſay, that any other liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is taken from them, but a libertie of doing euill. By theſe conſiderations it is more then manifeſt, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> makes no account of any extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as by inſtituting of lawes, by adminiſtring that iuſtice which God by the power of a ſupreme temporall Prince hath put into her hands: neither hath ſhe ſo deſerued to be proceeded againſt with Eccleſiaſticall cenſures; and ſo much the rather, becauſe theſe thundrings haue come foorth with ſuch expedition, that euery one which vnderſtandeth the courſes of <hi>Rome,</hi> may woonder from whence it ſhoud grow, that cauſes (yea and thoſe ſometime of ſmall moment) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in ſute ſo longtime in <hi>Rome,</hi> that moſt of them end rather with the death of the parties, then by the Iudges ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; and yet in a matter of ſuch conſequence, they haue proceeded not ſwiftly, but euen with precipice: For in the beginning of Nouemb. theſe matters were firſt mooued, and in fiue moneths it grew to ſuch a furious reſolution, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate a multitude of three millions of ſoules, and to interdict ſo great a circuit of ground and dominion, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when as with inſupportable impatience they attended alwaies this ſhort time with complaint, that ſome delay might be procured; and ſo to make vſe of the time. And his Holineſſe deſcended to ſuch a reſolution in making it onely knowne to the Cardinals, but without asking their opinion heerein, as commonly they doe, and principally in caſes of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17247:28"/> waightie importance, and not without ſome grudging of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> he being otherwiſe accuſtomed, not onely to acquaint the Cardinals with ſuch matters, but further to vſe their aduice and conſultation heerein. And af- that his laſt <hi>Breue</hi> of the 17. of Aprill, was decreed and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame day, he deliuered it openly in the Conſiſtorie, and proceeded immediately to intimation, and ſetting them vp: And in this alſo there is a matter of great wonder, for it being profeſſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> that no bodie elſe may ſend for the Proceſſe, and that great vigilancie ſhould be vſed in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the order, it running in euery mans mouth by way of a prouerbe; <hi>Omnis proceſſus formatus exira Curiam, vt pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm eſt nulliu;</hi> yet in a matter of ſo great moment, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded without citation. But they ſay, that this is <hi>de iure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> and they haue euer in their mouthes, <hi>Adam vbi es? &amp; vbi eſt Abel frater tuus?</hi> and yet we ſee heerein this was not obſerued. But if any man ſay, that the two <hi>Breues</hi> of the 10 of December, might ſerue for a ſufficient citation, there are three things which contradict this: the firſt is; that thoſe two firſt <hi>Breues</hi> of the tenth of December, are alſo tainted with this incurable diſeaſe: for in one of them declaring the nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the Senats lawes, and that they who made them, had incurred cenſure, they could not well come to this point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a citation, to deliuer their reaſons for the contrarie. Moreouer, admonition is one thing, and citation an other, as the Ciuilians very well teach vs; the one peremptorilie commands obedience, as in a matter already decided; and the other requires but a diſcuſſion to know whether it be well and neceſſarie, or that we are bound to obey: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe <hi>Breues</hi> commanding a reuokement of lawes, and a conſignation of priſoners, vnder peace, cenſure, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, they cannot be called citatorie, but monitorie: and it cannot be ſaid, that they runne in the tenour of a citation, they hauing no expreſſe tearme, nor time ſet downe; but they enioined execution immediately. As alſo we cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the Monitorie was conuertible into the nature
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17247:28"/> of a citation, becauſe it expreſſed the tearme of 24. daies; for by it the ſtatutes of the Common-wealth were fruſtrate and inefficacious, not after theſe 24. daies expired, but euen at the day, of the 17 of Aprill: wherfore ſuch alike annihilation cannot in any ſort be conuerted into a citation. And ſo much leſſe in reſpect of the reſt, there wanting in the ſame, a clauſe iuſtificatiue, without which it cannot onely not be conuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into a citation; but further, the Monitory it ſelfe, <hi>ipſo iure,</hi> is nothing, together with the excommunication, as <hi>Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> prooueth at large vpon the chap: <hi>Cum contingat;</hi> 8 <hi>cauſa nullitatis.</hi> And yet if we yeeld to all theſe defects, where ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth any citation or admonition vpon the law of 1602? which men ſay concerned goods enfiteoticall;<note place="margin">Rent charge.</note> and which ſurely is more, vpon cenſuall goods or leaſes, for a long time; the which notwithſtanding hath firſt place in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitorie, and is annulled without ſo much as vnderſtanding what the true meaning of it was, or with what reaſon it might be defended; if they had firſt, at leaſt but heard ſome ſpeech of it, or if ſome extraiudiciall diſcuſſion had beene vſed heerein, why this had beene ſomewhat; but that it ſhould ſo ſuddenly and ſpeedily be condemned, before it was conceiued or vnderſtood, this is a great and moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous wonder.</p>
            <p>It may be it is not ſo requiſite to extend into a diſcourſe concerning the deſert of this cauſe of <hi>Enfiteuſi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning is mentioned.</note> ſeeing ſuch a notable error was committed euen in iudiciall place and calling: but becauſe ſome peraduenture will deſire to haue a ſummarie vnderſtanding of the Common-wealths reaſons heerein; it will not be much from the purpoſe, briefly to touch ſome of them, by which we may cleerely conceiue the lawfull authority which the Senate had for the iuſtifying of ſuch a law; the neceſſitie that vrged them thereunto, and the equitie of the thing inſtituted, and ſo incidently we may diſcerne an error, which either purpoſely or by chance crept into the vnderſtanding of the words, and cauſe of this law.</p>
            <p>The Pope ſaies in his Monitorie, that the Duke and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17247:29"/> on the 23 of May 1602, taking occaſion vpon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie occurring betwixt Doctor <hi>Franceſco Zaberella,</hi> of the one part, and the Monks of <hi>Pragia</hi> of the other, they did not onely enact, that the Monkes either then, or in any time to come, ought not to pretend plea vnder any title whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, to be preferred to enfiteoticall goods, poſſeſſed by the Laietie, nor obtaine propertie in the ſaid goods, by the claimes, prelation, conſolidation, or extinction of direct line, or vpon any other title whatſoeuer, their direct right or freehold reſerued;<note place="margin">All theſe were in the beginning expreſſed.</note> but that the force of this law alſo was intended and firmely to be extended ouer all other Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall or religious places.</p>
            <p>From this it cannot appeere whether his Holineſſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the order of the Senate; foraſmuch as it extendeth to all places and perſons Eccleſiaſticall, which was decided, in the cauſe betweene the Monkes and the Doctors, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing notwithſtanding this foreſaid deciſion, in a particular controuerſie; or whether it may be conſtrued, that he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends together both the one and other: For granting that the Senate had lawfull power to end that ſute, and to denie that they could ordaine by a generall law, that the ſame ſhould be vnderſtood and intended vpon any other ſuch like caſe occurring, I cannot ſee how a man but of indifferent capacitie, can any waies conceiue it; conſidering it is a moſt euident thing, that it belongeth to the ſame power to make a law vpon an occaſion, and to iudge particular controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies occurring in the ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polyt</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſheweth that iudgment is but a particular law, and the law a generall iudgement: and that it would be ſufficient if a Iudge could be found without all partialitie; or the law would of it ſelfe be preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent enough, if it could comprehend al particular caſes. And in <hi>Iuſtinians codex</hi> we ſee,<note place="margin">L. <hi>3.</hi> t <hi>5.</hi> ne quis in ſua.</note> that iuriſdiction comprehendeth two heads, that is, either <hi>iudicare,</hi> or <hi>ius dicere,</hi> the one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to the inſtituting of that, whereon ſentence may be grounded; and the other in pronouncing the ſame. In <hi>Rome</hi> the Proctors office was to make generall edicts, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17247:29"/> Iudges, who conformable to them, might giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in particular cauſes. If the law were ſpirituall, and the Iudge Secular, it could not be vnderſtood how he might iudge according to the ſame. Spirituall ſcience, and worldly action had no correſpondencie: the Philoſophers ſay, that the rule muſt be <hi>homogenea,</hi> with that ruled; for which cauſe the Ciuilians affirme with all reaſon, <hi>Forum ſortiri, &amp; ſtatutis ligari paria ſunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pau. Caſt. l. omnes populi, ff. de instit. &amp; iur.</note> Wherefore he which conſents that the Senate hath lawfully determined the cauſe betweene the Monkes and the Doctor, he muſt needes alſo grant them power to decree that in generall, which hath beene ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled in iudgement giuen, and ought ſo to be in all others that ſhall occurre.</p>
            <p>But if it be vnderſtood to reprehend alſo the examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and end made by the Senate,<note place="margin">Decius c. quae in Eccleſiarum, &amp;c. Eccleſia San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Mariae, de const<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t. Alex. conſ. <hi>201.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> in the caſe betweene the Monks and the Doctor, this may be; which manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth how requiſit it was, not to haue beene ſo forward, but at firſt to haue framed a Monitory, and principally vpon this point, before ſeeing the proceſſe framed in the ſute, and controuerſie aboue mentioned.</p>
            <p>Conſidering it is not true that the Doctor was plaintife in that caſe, and the Monks defendants, as the Monitorie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth; it running thus; <hi>inter doctorem, &amp;c. ex vna, &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachas, &amp;c. ex altera partibus.</hi> of the one partie, and the Monkes of the other partie.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Corſato de Corſati,</hi> in 1598, hauing bought of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drea Monaldo</hi> eight fields which paied canonate to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie of <hi>Pragia,</hi> the Doctour 1602. the 12. of Februarie, tendred the price, to make his draft by border or confine: and the ſecond of March, the Monkes pretending to be preferred to him, as Patrons of the free-hold of thoſe fields, they came before the <hi>Podeſta</hi> of <hi>Padoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Like our Maior.</note> and commenced ſute, pretending prelation; in which cauſe many actions were tried before the Magiſtrate; till according to the cuſtome of this State, by the Doctors &amp; Communaltie of <hi>Paduaes</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, the hearing of the matter was referred ouer to the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17247:30"/> Senate. The Doctor drew not the Monaſterie to a Laie iudgement; but the Eccleſiaſticks themſelues knew well, that the determining of this cauſe belonged vnto a Secular Iudge; for this cauſe they had recourſe to the ſame: the which one example onely, if there had beene no other, gaue iuriſdiction to the <hi>Podeſta,</hi> and conſequently to the Senate in that cauſe, as in expreſſe words it is declared; <hi>in l. prima, C. de iuriſd. omn. iudic.</hi> But beſides this firme and ſolide foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, we may adde another very preualent and vniuerſall, which is, that from time out of minde, much before 200. yeeres laſt paſt, when any plea hath beene of goods poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Laietie, (giue them the name of emphyteoticall, cenſuall, feudatorie, leaſe for long time, or what other title ſoeuer) the Eccleſiaſticall Iudge in this State hath neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced iudgement therein; but alwaies and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, the hearing and iuriſdiction thereof hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Secular. So that by this, wee doe not onely prooue, that the controuerſies betweene the Monks and the Doctor was iuridically determined by the Senate; but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that a power is proper to them, to make ſtatutes, which may diſpoſe and order of thoſe goods aboue named, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Laietie, wherein the Church hath directly free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; for vnto them it hath and doth appertaine, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe controuerſies, which haue or doe ariſe about them; and aboue we haue made cleere demonſtration, how it ſtandeth with the ſame power to make ſtatutes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce iudgements. There remaine regiſters in all the Chanceries of this citie, of iudgements giuen by a Secular Iudge ſince they haue beene ſubiect to this State; and not one can be produced which was tried in an Eccleſiaſticall Court. And it cannot be tearmed an vſurpation, ſeeing the Clergie haue not beene drawne to theſe Courts, as defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts but they haue voluntarily appeared as plaintifes: &amp; that which ouerthroweth this claime more then any thing elſe, is; that in ſuch controuerſies betweene Church and Church, they themſelues haue appeared in the Secular Court, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17247:30"/> Iuſtice againſt another Church. Nay and out of doubt it may certainly be beleeued, that the beginning of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction hath beene very Canonicall, ſeeing the Clergie of that time were alſo very good men, and zealous in the Churches behoofes; and in like maner the Popes were moſt exact mainteiners of the Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction: and ſo as well the one as the other, knew very well the title of that ground for which they came in ſute before the Secular; nor none of them euer reprehended this courſe of iudgement, but rather ſecurely we may affirme, that they themſelues haue brought it in. And there is an expreſſe conſtitution of <hi>Iuſtinians,</hi> that cuſtome alone giues as great iuriſdiction as a law made.</p>
            <p>But in that his Holineſſe ſaith in his Monitorie,<note place="margin">C. de eman. lib. l. vlt.</note> that the Senats ordinance conſtituteth <hi>in bonis Eccleſiaſticis emphyteo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis,</hi> it muſt neceſſarily be, that either his miniſters haue had ſome other copie or writing, then the true originall, or elſe that tranſported with affection, they ſuppoſed they ſaw that in it, which cannot be found neither in words nor ſenſe; becauſe that <hi>emphyteoticis,</hi> is not there either formally or in equiualent words; and they can no waies excuſe themſelues by ſaying they thought that the ſenſe had beene ſo, as they haue expreſſed it: that it is not lawfull to relate an other mans ſpeech in other words, but eſpecially in ſuch a manner as to reſtraine that to one kinde, which was ſpoken general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. The law ſaith; that Churches may not appropriate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues, goods poſſeſſed by the Laietie, their direct title and right notwithſtanding reſerued. It is not true, that there is diſtinction of <hi>directum,</hi> and <hi>vtile</hi> onely in <hi>Emfiteuſi,</hi> but both theſe claimes concur in patrimoniall goods, both the which are treated of in a title of the ſecond booke of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinians Codex,</hi> whoſe direct right may lie in the Church,<note place="margin">tit. de ſun. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim. L. ſiquis fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos. L. fundi patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniales. L. hi quibus.</note> if the Prince haue giuen them it: and although this maner of poſſeſſing was out of vſe in <hi>Italy</hi> vnder the French Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and their ſucceſſors, and inſtead thereof, there hath come in fee-ſimple; yet doth there remaine in Churches
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17247:31"/> but eſpecially thoſe cathedrall, ſome goods of this nature which were giuen before the Emperours of <hi>Constantinople</hi> were wholly excluded from the Empire of theſe adiacent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; in leaſe perpetuall or perpetuities, there is <hi>directum</hi> and <hi>vtile:</hi> where notwithſtanding (as alſo in the lands aboue mentioned) neither relation nor conſolidation, nor extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of line take any place, as <hi>Couaruuias,</hi> and <hi>Valaſco,</hi> who are cited by many Doctors, doe effectually prooue; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome not very circumſpect hold the contrarie.</p>
            <p>A great part of the direct titles of Churches in theſe low Countries neere the ſea, which ſometimes were mariſhes and vallies, are of this kinde: for this ſoile being altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water, and reaping no fruit from it, but reeds and flags, they were let out for euer, or at leaſt for a wonderfull long time, at a verie eaſie rent, anſwerable to the profits that they yeelded, though now through the wonderfull charge of the Secular, both publike and priuate, in raiſing of the ground, drenching of the mariſhes, and draning of the water; they haue beene reduced to the State wherein they are: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Church hath no reaſon in this, neither by written euidence, equitie of pretending prelation, deuolution, or vnder any other claime to appropriate them to themſelues; and of theſe the law of the Senate, in a great part entreateth, as alſo it conſtituteth vpon other kinde of goods, as ſhall be expreſſed.</p>
            <p>For it muſt needs be, that a penſion was paied to the Church, either by the claime of a reſeruatiue cenſe or impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or that the Church in ancient times vpon ſutes made, haue couenanted this reſeruation, or that hauing beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by other Lords the ſellers, it was afterwards giuen to the Church by them: In which caſe, this reſerued cenſe or taxe, out of doubt belongeth to the Church <hi>in perpetuum:</hi> but ouer the poſſeſſion ſtable, there remaines in no ſort any title vnto them, by vertue of which they may pretend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolidation, prelation, couenant, or other ſuch like actions.</p>
            <p>Fee-ſimple is alſo of this nature, that in it direct title is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17247:31"/> diſtinguiſhed from profits; and I wonder, when they would needs adde to the law of the Senate, and declare it in another ſenſe then the truth therof imported, with that word <hi>Emphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teoticis,</hi> why to change and adulterate it the more, they ſaid not, <hi>Feudalibus:</hi> but peraduenture they would not proceed ſo farre, becauſe they could not hope it would neuer be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it being a vulgar word, and well vnderſtood of all men.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Emphyteoticis,</hi> is ſomewhat more vnknowne, and therefore was thought the fitter to be ſecretly put in; and therefore I cannot forbeare to replie, that in the Senats law the word <hi>Emphyteotici,</hi> is not vſed, but it generally ſpeakes of all contracts, and manner of poſſeſſion, wherein the two titles of <hi>directum</hi> and <hi>vtile</hi> ſtand diuided; neither is it lawfull for any body to reſtraine or expreſſe it, contrary to the true ſenſe thereof, to the end, the better to bring in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on following, ſet downe in the Monitorie, which otherwiſe could not haue beene deduced: <hi>Cùm praemiſſa in aliquibus ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum iura, etiam ex contractibus initis ipſis ecclesijs compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, auſerant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no new matter, that the Spiritualtie, to enter vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on goods poſſeſſed of Seculars, haue aſſayed to bring in this name of <hi>Enfiteuſi</hi> into their titles, by which they receiue a canon or penſion: but two hundred yeeres agoe, diuers cities of <hi>Italy</hi> haue ſtood out againſt them for this cauſe; and they themſelues haue otherwhiles beene conſtrained to giue ouer their pretences and titles, and to be contented with their bare canon comming in.</p>
            <p>In the ſame citie of <hi>Padoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Extant au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentica capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula tranſact.</note> about an hundred and fiftie yeres ſince, great controuerſies grew betwixt that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty &amp; the Monks of <hi>S. Iuſtina,</hi> and <hi>Pragia,</hi> vpon this point, the which they ended by comprimiſe; where amongſt other things it was ſet downe, that in all their goods, neither eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheat, prelation, nor conſolidation for di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect line extinct, ſhould take any place, as the citie then conſtantly auerred, that from time out of minde, it had beene the vſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the place.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:17247:32"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Paula Caſ. l. Conſil. <hi>244.</hi>
               </note>In <hi>Vrbine</hi> alſo before that time, there fell out a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie betwixt the Clergie and the people, the which was likewiſe ended by comprimiſe, with an expreſſe declaration that conſolidation vpon line extinct, ſhould neuer take place. A little before that alſo, there grew very dangerous tumults in <hi>Ferrara,</hi> about this very point; for pacification of which, Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9. rather as a Soueraigne Prince, then as a Pope, not out of fauour, but by iuſtice was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, in fees, <hi>Emfiteuſi,</hi> and other ſuch like contracts, within the territories of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> to take away eſcheate, prelation, with conſolidation, <hi>per lineam finitam,</hi> and to ſet downe a new forme, correſpondent to equitie and iuſtice, which might reduce them more to the nature of Cenſes, then of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other tenor; and the Doctors alſo perceiuing the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dammage the Laietie receiued by deuolution, or conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidation by line extinct, out of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion, they abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely remooued it; affirming that in ſuch a caſe, the neereſt kinſman collaterall might claime by iuſtice to be inueſted therein,<note place="margin">Vide Clar. &amp; Valaſc. Ruin. conſ. <hi>12.</hi> vol. <hi>1.</hi> Decius conſil. <hi>131.</hi> Bero conſ. <hi>98.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> Abbas c. bonae, de poſtul. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. &amp; conſil. <hi>113.</hi> Curt. Sen. cap. <hi>47.</hi> Riminal. cap. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> and being denied, he might appeale; and many grow to this ſpecification, that the Church ſought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croch vpon the ſtable poſſeſſion it ſelfe; and alſo others an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe heereunto, that they are not bound to grant the inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture, but further that they cannot improue nor enhance the Canon.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder if by a law or ſolemne comprimiſe in the places aboue named, caducitie for Canon not paied, prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in caſe of ſale, and conſolidation for line extinct, are taken away, conſidering that none of theſe are neceſſarie, or eſſentiall in a contract. But whatſoeuer may be done by a law, may be performed by a deed, as alſo cuſtome may bring it in; For which cauſe a long and preſcript cuſtome time out of minde, this State was of force an hundred and fiftie yeeres ſince, to take away from a little emphyteoticall ſubſtance, (prouided if there then were any) caducitie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and conſolidation; and furthet to introduce, that more then the paiment of a penſion, they ſhould be held for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17247:32"/> patrimoniall and leaſable. Wee may ſee the 72. Conſ. of <hi>Panormitano,</hi> where he diſcourſeth at large, that cuſtome was alſo of that force in Eccleſiaſticall emphyteuſi to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in the citie of <hi>Vrbine,</hi> that the condition of caducitie was vtterly remooued. The which notwithſtanding were more profitable for the Church; for by this the Church ſhould gaine the improuements without paying them, the which by prelation, conſolidation, or line extinct, they could not appropriate to themſelues, without paying them at a iuſt rate; whereupon by an argument <hi>a ſimili,</hi> and alſo <hi>a maiore,</hi> ſo much the rather may cuſtome take away prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſolidation. We may adde heereunto, that it is not peculiar to this State, that ſome goods emphyteoticall ſhould be made leaſable; but alſo in <hi>France</hi> all <hi>Emfiteuſi</hi> are made ſuch, as <hi>Ioan. Rub. Auth. Ingreſſi, de Sacroſanctis Ecclesijs</hi> teſtifieth. All which things doe euidently ſhew the equitie and neceſſitie of ſuch a law. The which, though the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Senate did not conſtitute at that time, in forme of a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten law, publiſhed through their whole State, in generall tearmes; yet notwithſtanding they haue by vſe, cuſtome, and writing alſo, in cauſes occurrent, made, obſerued, and executed the ſame, from that time hitherto.</p>
            <p>There are many Decrees of the Princes of this Common-wealth, with their Colledge, which from time to time in controuerſies occurring betwixt the Church and the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, or betweene Church and Church, haue beene reſolued and determined, not to admit of caducitie, prelation, or conſolidation of profits with the free-hold; and ſometimes they haue put into their euidences generall clauſes, which might comprehend all theſe caſes, as in Duke <hi>Vendra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos</hi> daies, in 1476. in a reſcript made to the <hi>Podeſta</hi> of <hi>Monſelice,</hi> vpon ſuch a particular controuerſie, theſe words were added; <hi>nunquam pati volumus (etiam in bonis Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, quenquam, qui diu tenuerit agrum aliquem iure liuelli, quem ſumptibus, &amp; laboribus ſuis meliorauerit, ſic de facto expoliari, ſed tantùm quòd ſoluat liuellos non ſolutos:</hi> and in Duke <hi>Moroes</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17247:33"/> time, in other reſcript to the Rectors of <hi>Breſcia</hi> the yeere 1466, hauing excluded the Abbat of <hi>Leno</hi> from withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of his liuellarie goods ſolde vnto others, there is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; <hi>Et de hac noſtra intentione, date dicto Abbati notitiam, &amp; declarate, ne contra eam dictos Chriſtopherum, &amp; Cornelium inquietet, ſed acquieſcat huic voluntati noſtrae, quia hoc idem in alijs terris &amp; locis noſtris ſeruari volumus, &amp; facimus in ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">C. de leg. l. ſi Imperialis. Afflict. d. <hi>313.</hi> Menoch. vide conſ. <hi>676.</hi> nu. <hi>2. 487.</hi> nu. <hi>3. 973.</hi> n. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note>From which we may cleerely collect, that this is no new law, but from ancient times by cuſtome eſtabliſhed, and alſo confirmed, not only by the particular iudgemets of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but by the Prince himſelfe. Of which the law thus ſpeaketh: <hi>Si cauſam Princeps inter partes cognouerit, &amp; ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam dixerit, eſt lex in omnibus ſimilibus:</hi> and according to the Ciuilians, they retaine the vigor of a law, though they were but deciſiue only in a particular caſe; as indeed all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non lawes are but in a maner the deciſions of particular ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but ſo much the rather, when they are further ioyned with a ſignification of the Princes will in ſuch like caſes, with an explanation thereof in generall tearmes, as in the aboue ſpecified. And theſe things were performed by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; not only the Clergie, who were repulſed in their demands, but the Nuncioes Apoſtolicall alſo: and ſo conſequently, the Popes themſelues ſeeing and vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much, yet neuer repealing them, and therefore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly approouing them for iuſt, and neceſſarie to be put in execution. So that what the Senate did deliberate 1602, is a declaration and expreſſion in writing of an old law, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined by cuſtome, and mentioned in direct writings to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Magiſtrates, euen as alſo in the ſelfe ſame law it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declared in theſe words: The ſeruice of our affaires, for the quiet and comfort of our ſubiects, requireth that this ſute be determined in ſuch a maner, as not onely in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion of <hi>Zabarella,</hi> but that for euer, vpon any other of the like nature, it ſhall not be determined differently from the good cuſtome and iudgements often times denounced,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17247:33"/> conformable to the ſame. I will not omit to adde, that if there had beene the leaſt ſcruple of offence in that law, Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight, during whoſe Papacie it was publiſhed, being a very zealous Pope, and one that in this citie had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vigilant miniſters, would neuer haue diſſembled it.</p>
            <p>And if the tenor of this ordinance hath beene read, it yet ſeemes very requiſite, that hearing cuſtome, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo often to be named therein, they ſhould firſt haue ſeene and vnderſtood, what cuſtome and iudgements thoſe were. What is he of ſo meane an intellect, which ſees not how this proceeding hath beene without vnderſtanding the cauſe, and that many particularities haue beene purpoſely kept backe by them, which ſhould haue beene related to his Holineſſe, for verification of this act; they conceiuing well that all theſe things were neceſſarie to be vnderſtood, before the comming to treat an execution? But it ſeemes there was ſuch a ſpeciall deſire that theſe thundrings ſhould come forth, as for feare of meeting with ſomewhat which might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert it, they ſhunned the verie ſight of any thing that might remooue his Holineſſe minde from ſuch a deliberation.</p>
            <p>If the intended breuitie of this preſent diſcourſe would permit, it ſhould euidently be made knowne, how beyond all reaſon, it is ſaid in the Monitorie, hauing reference to this law, as it appeares: <hi>Cum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praemiſſa in aliquibus Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum iura, etiam ex contractibus initis ipſis Ecclesijs competentia auferant.</hi> As alſo withall, it would be cleere, that by that law there is no <hi>ius quaeſitum</hi> taken from the Church, nay, and which is more, the ſame continuing in vigor and force, there remaines ſtill to the Church a moſt eaſie and readie way to retaine <hi>omnia iura quaeſita ſibi competentia.</hi> It was neuer the cuſtome of this Common-wealth, to take away <hi>ius quaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> from any body whoſoeuer, much leſſe from the Church; but he that will iudge of others lawes without er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, it is neceſſarie that he firſt vnderſtand and haue full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of them, &amp; not to proceed to their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before he haue ſo much as lookt into their foundations.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17247:34"/> I haue ſpoken more of this matter, then was conuenient for this diſcourſe, yet is it not the leaſt part, in reſpect of that which remaines behinde.</p>
            <p>And if occaſion be offered, to make knowne the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this law, euerie one ſhall perceiue, how it is grounded vpon iuſtice and equitie, and how lawfull the authoritie of the Senate was to conſtitute it.</p>
            <p>Now let vs returne againe to deliuer that which yet hath beene vnſpoken of, concerning the matters aboue diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of. If the Pope preuented of his more mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would not admit of reaſons ſo cleere and euident as thoſe before declared, and ſo to haue iuſtified the cauſe of the Common-wealth: yet at leaſt perceiuing that all <hi>Europe</hi> had lawes like vnto theſe, which he ſo ſharpely reprehended, and that ſuch a number of approoued Doctors hold a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie opinion to himſelfe, hee might haue held the caſe doubtfull, and haue proceeded with circumſpection; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde that excommunication, is a grieuous penalty, and an odious matter; and as the Canoniſts affirme, <hi>Sirictiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè interpretanda.</hi> Neither is it vnderſtood that any one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs the ſame, when the words of the Canon are ambiguous or generall, the which may not be wrung to an other caſe, by way of ſimilitude, and much leſſe with an argument <hi>a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori:</hi> For if one giue a Prieſt a boxe on the eare, he is excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; but if he ſhoot an harquebuſſe at him, and that in the Church, and hit him not, he is not excommunicated for this, though the ſecond offence is an hundred times greater then the firſt. Let it be granted, that whoſoeuer makes ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes againſt Eccleſiaſticall libertie, <hi>ipſo facto</hi> is excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated. This point muſt alſo be cleared, whether the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian ſtatutes be againſt the libertie of the Church; and it hath beene prooued with moſt effectuall reaſons, that they are not; the which alſo though they were, it appeareth by act, and not by diſcourſe, that the like lawes haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued all <hi>Europe</hi> ouer: and we ſee in Print, how many wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters doe iuſtifie them. Then this is out of doubt at leaſt, that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17247:34"/> they are not abſolutely againſt the Popes authoritie, as it is ſuppoſed. Vnto which let me annex this; that being not yet decided, what Eccleſiaſticall libertie is, as hath beene ſaid, and the Doctors not agreeing thereupon, much leſſe can they be out of doubt, that theſe lawes and acts are againſt it. But for al this, in a matter, of which according to ſome mens opinions, there is controuerſie, and that in ſo many points remaines doubtful, out comes me headlong an Interdict or exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, without foreſeeing, or maturely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the inconueniences, which ſaith the Chap.<note place="margin">De ſentent. excom. in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alma Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> enſue of ſuch cenſures; that is, the people loſe their deuotion, hereſies are brooded, infinite dangers grow to mens ſoules, and without the peoples fault due ſeruice is taken away from the Church. Surely Chriſtian pietie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the woorthineſſe of this cauſe ſhould firſt with all diligence haue beene examined, neither ſhould leſſe then a good opinion at leaſt haue beene borne towards a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth ſo pious and deuout. Euery Prelate is bound firſt, in himſelfe to conceiue the woorthineſſe of the cauſe, and then with Chriſtian loue to acquaint others with the ſame; and as <hi>S. Paul</hi> teacheth, <hi>in ſpiritu lenitatis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> the which as it would haue produced ſome excellent effect, being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; ſo being neglected, it hath cauſed great euill, which now may alreadie be ſeene, and further greater dangers, which ſtill hang ouer our heads.</p>
            <p>The Pope in his Monitorie of the 17 of Aprill ſaith; that the Duke and Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> haue many yeeres paſt made ſundry ſtatutes, through which they did incurre cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but amongſt others, he ſpecially names three, vpon which he diſcendeth to fulmination, except they be reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked within foure and twentie daies. Euery good Chriſtian may heere deſire to vnderſtand, that ſeeing a great number of different and ſundry ſtatutes haue beene made by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to the ſoules preiudice, and that for euery one of theſe, ſhe hath incurred Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound, to caſhiere and annihilate them all: why is the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17247:35"/> Senate told but onely of three? We neither can nor muſt beleeue, that the other would be omitted for the damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſoules, and therefore at this preſent why are they not all treated of? When any one meetes his owne debtor, hee may aske him a part of his debt, and as he is principall, hee may remit the reſt, or the whole: but an agent or factor, can not doe this, except by a commiſſion from the principall. If diuers and ſundry ſtatutes made ſome yeeres ſince, offend God, the Common-wealth is bound to reuoke them all, and in but reuoking of three, they ſhould not ſufficiently diſcharge their dutie.<note place="margin">Iac. 2.</note> 
               <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith; <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> totam legem ſeruauerit, offendat autem in vno, factus eſt omnium reus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour commanded the vſe of excommunication for ſinnes, which procure the ſoules preiudice, when he ſaith; <hi>Si peccauerit in te frater tuus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 17.</note> and <hi>S. Paul</hi> expreſſeth what theſe were, ſaying; <hi>Si is qui frater nominatur eſt fornicator, aut auarus, aut idolis ſeruiens, aut maledicus, aut ebrioſiu, aut ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pax, cum huiuſmodi nec cibum ſumere.</hi> Wherefore at this preſent we may alledge what the Sonne of God ſometimes ſaid;<note place="margin">Matth 23.</note> 
               <hi>Vae vobis, qui decimatis mentam, &amp; anetum, &amp; cimmum, &amp; reliquiſtis quae grauiora ſunt, legis iudicium, &amp; miſericordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; fidem: haec oportuit facere, &amp; illa non omittere.</hi> Out of which we may anſwer plentifully to that which is contained in the Monitorie, that the lawes and decrees of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth were, <hi>in perniciem animarum.</hi> And moreouer, if it had inferred, that the actions of the Common-wealth were in <hi>in ſcandalum plurimorum;</hi> they muſt take heed leſt they conclude quite contrarie to that they would. Out of queſtion, we ought diligently to extirpate all things ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, but eſpecially if they be of badde edification vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but we neuer heard, that any hath beene ſcandalized by ſeeing offenders chaſtized and puniſhed, that diſturbe the publike peace, or to ſee auarice and luxurie bridled. It ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breedeth ſcandall to ſee a wicked fellow walke through the citie; when his companions in the ſame offence were executed: and ſo conſequently to ſee one ſued by the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17247:35"/> of the Church, whoſe puniſhment aboue all other, the Church ſhould rather haue procured. And it bootes not to extend farre, in manifeſting what things are ſcandalous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery one is priuie to himſelfe, wherein he giueth or receiueth ſcandall; and thoſe alſo that in ſome ſort defend things of bad inſtruction, they doe it not without blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and feeling in their owne conſciences that they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the trueth.</p>
            <p>It is true that this Monitorie was made after the example of ten Popes more, which therein are named, and his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is to be commended in imitating of them; but ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, an hundred others his moſt Holie predeceſſors are woorthie of no leſſe commendations, which neuer gaue the leaſt ſigne, that euer it came into their thought, that they might diſanull the lawes of Princes, made for publike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: but rather they haue publiſhed and executed the ſame alſo; and when they met with any ſcruple in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings and iuſtice, they haue with great dexteritie and charitie ſought to make knowne vnto their Princes, what Gods will heerein hath beene. In this maner <hi>S. Damaſe</hi> publiſhed &amp; executed <hi>Valentinians</hi> law: and <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> one made by <hi>Mauritius,</hi> wherin a ſouldier was prohibited to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Monke. Further the denouncing of an excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſentence againſt an whole Senate, which is not a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon, is far from the doctrine of the ancient &amp; beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> cont. Ep. Permen. <hi>23.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> c. non poteſt.</note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> holds an excomunication againſt an whole multitude, though it were for ſome notorious and manifeſt ſinne, too ſacrilegious, pernicious, impious, and inſolent (for theſe are his formall words:) and he aduiſeth good Paſtors in thoſe caſes to haue recourſe vnto God, with ſighes and prayers: a place intreated of by that Saint at large;<note place="margin">Two ſcurrile writers. <hi>q</hi> 22. <hi>a.</hi> 5. <hi>in add. &amp; in</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 18. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>a.</hi> 3. <hi>quol.</hi> 10. 15</note> and with ſuch a ſpirit, as if it were read inſtead of <hi>Barbaccia,</hi> or <hi>Zen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelino,</hi> it would produce a verie charitable ſpirit in euerie Chriſtian minde; which the reading of the others will neuer doe. <hi>S. Thomas</hi> putteth a queſtion, whether any Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie may be excommunicated; and he anſwers himſelfe,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17247:36"/> No: and produceth reaſons for the ſame, concluding that the Church appointed with great prouidence, that no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie might be excommunicated: &amp; all other Diuines with accord determine the ſame. As alſo Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth in the Chap.<note place="margin">De ſentent. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> ſaith thus; <hi>In vniuerſitatem, vel Collegium proferri ſententiam excommunicationis penitus prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere;</hi> where the Gloſe debates whether a ſentence of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication denounced againſt a Communitie would be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidious or no, &amp; he alledgeth foure famous Doctors which affirme that it would not, and he voucheth one of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie part: in the end he comes to this point; that it ſhould not indeed be denounced; but if the denunciation were paſt, he holds it ſecureſt to take it for validious. In this argument they all agree, that ſuch an excommunication ought not to be thundred out; many ſay alſo, that being denounced, it is nothing: and ſome few after fulmination, hold it preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. It belongs to a religious and godly conſcience, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the opinion of the moſt famous, the beſt grounded, and that which is eſtabliſhed by Pontificall conſtitution, or that fauoureth pietie moſt; and not that generally condemned by the Doctors, ſeeing thoſe few alſo which repute it true, giue no aduice to follow the ſame. And that which we read in all the books of the Canoniſts, cannot be oppoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>Papa non poteſt errare;</hi> the which propoſition was ſoundly vnderſtood by him that firſt deliuered it, and was limited onely to matters of faith, in decreeing and determining; not in ſuppoſing or thinking; and being to ſpeake, the Pope was to vſe the due meanes of diuine inuocation and aſſiſtance. At this preſent, adulation, remoouing the true limits, carries it away abſolutely for true, although the effects were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes quite contrarie. <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelfe may ſerue for an example;<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> who after that Chriſt had ſaid vnto him, <hi>tibi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo claues Regni Coelorum,</hi> immediately he fell a reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our Sauiour himſelfe, becauſe he would be crucified; wherefore our Lord ſaid vnto him; <hi>Vade poſt me Sathanas, ſcandalum es mihi, quia non ſapis quae Dei ſunt, ſed quae homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:17247:36"/> His deniall alſo is ſo well knowen to euery one, that it imports not to recite it. And <hi>S. Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Galathians, ſayth; <hi>Cum veniſſet Cephas Antiochiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 2. Gen. 2.</note> 
               <hi>in faciem ei reſtiti, quia reprehenſibilis erat.</hi> And <hi>S. Peters</hi> example is not alone by it ſelfe; for if <hi>Cam</hi> had not beene reprehended for diſcouering his father <hi>Noahs</hi> nakedneſſe, three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Popes might be produced ſubiect not only to ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in their priuate cuſtomes, but in their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and doctrine alſo; and if any man pleaſe to reade the liues of the Popes after the yeere 890, for an hundred &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres following, without looking after ſome others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed; he will diſcerne that to be moſt true,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> which <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth; <hi>Omnis Pontifex ex hominibus aſſumptus, pro hominibus conſtituitur in his, quae ſunt ad Deum, vt offerat dona, &amp; ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia pro peccatis, qui condolere poſſit ijs, qui ignorant, &amp; errant, quoniam &amp; ipſe circundatus eſt infirmitate.</hi> So that <hi>S. Boniface</hi> the Martyr ſayd not without iuſt cauſe; <hi>Si Papa ſuae &amp; frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſalutis negligens deprehenditur, inutilis, &amp; remiſſus in operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis, &amp; inſuper a bono taciturnus, quod magis officit ſibi, &amp; omnibus, nihilominus innumerabiles populos cateruatim ſecum ducit, primo mancipio gehennae cum ipſo plagis multis in aeternum vapulaturus. Huius culpas iſtic redarguere praeſumit mortalium nullus, quia cunctos ipſe iudicaturus à nemine eſt iudicandus; niſi deprehendatur à fide deuius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not take it for ſuch a great woonder, that one Pope with his decrees and cenſures hath offended or iniured another, nor repute it ſuch a ſinne to ſay, that he ought alſo to amend his owne errors committed: for not only religious and godly Popes, but thoſe alſo that were lead moſt of all by humane meanes and policie, haue confeſſed that they might erre, and offered themſelues to reclamation. <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth entreating of a controuerſie betwixt him and the Emperour, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Second, vſeth theſe words; <hi>Si Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia cùm in aliquo contra debitum laeſerat, quod non credebant, parata erat corrigere, ac in ſtatum debitum reformare, et ſi diceret ipſe quod in nullo, contra iuſtitiam, laeſerat Eccleſiam, vel quod
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17247:37"/> nos eum contra iuſtitiam laeſiſſemus, parati eramus vocare Reges, Praelatos, &amp; Principes tam Eccleſiaſticos quàm ſeculares ad ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem tutum locum, vbi per ſe, vel per ſolemnes nuncios conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, eratque parata Eccleſia de conſilio concilij ſibi ſatisfacere, ſi eum laeſiſſet in aliquo, ac reuocare ſententiam, ſi quam contra ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum iniuſtè tuliſſet, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſentence therefore of Excommunication hauing beene thundred out againſt the Duke and Senate, and all their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions interdicted, becauſe they will not ſuffer the libertie of the Common-wealth to be defrauded; becauſe they giue not conſent for the cooping vp of the foundations whereon it is built; becauſe they doe not depriue her of the power granted by God, in the adminiſtration of the Common-wealth, ſo neceſſarie for to mainteine the tranquillitie and peace of her dominions; becauſe they defend the liues, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and goods of thoſe people committed to their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment; and to conclude, becauſe they haue euer, and now do that, which they are commanded by his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. And though this Excommunication was denounced without vnderſtanding the cauſe, without citation or obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of thoſe eſſentiall tearmes proper to iudgement, and ordeined by God in the law of Nature, with an affection, farre different from that which his diuine Maieſty comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, without due aduice, and flat againſt the doctrine of the holy Fathers, ſacred Diuines, and the Pontificiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions themſelues; yet remaines it to be conſidered vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for all the iniuſtice thereof is ſo cleere, and the nullitie perſpicuous and plaine, what the princes dutie in this caſe is, and how he ought to beare himſelfe herein before God and his holy Church.</p>
            <p>At the firſt ſight, ſomebody may aduiſe peraduenture, that it were good to follow herein the counſell of <hi>S. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: Sententia Paſtoris, ſiue iuſta, ſiue iniuſta timenda:</hi> and ſo to commend his cauſe vnto God, with aſſurance, that patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſupport vniuſt cenſures, will turne to his great merit before the Maieſtie of God. An excellent courſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17247:37"/> for an innocent, which could not ſhew the equitie of his owne cauſe; but for a Prince that hath ſo cleere and manifeſt reaſon on his ſide, a more pernicious way cannot be taken either for himſelfe, his State, or the ſeruice of God, which muſt be reſpected aboue all other things: For a Prince is more bound then a priuate man, to feare God, to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his holy faith, to reuerence Prelats, that he diſcharge Chriſt his place; but ſo he is more bound to auoid hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and ſuperſtition, to preſerue his dignitie, to maintaine his State in the exerciſe of Religion; to take heed leſt that do not happen to his people which ſometimes fell out to the Iewes, through <hi>Moſes</hi> long abſence, who thinking that in him they were depriued of the true God, they made them one of gold: a thing which if it were well conſidered, the world would not be at that paſſe which now it is. That ſaying is not ſo generally true; <hi>ſententia Paſtoris, ſiue iuſta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>11.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia.</note> 
               <hi>ſiue iniuſta ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda,</hi> as ſome Doctors interpret it, who haue introduced and would maintaine in the Church of God, a power which in name ſhould bee called Eccleſiaſticall, but in deed is Temporall.</p>
            <p>There is another Canon made by Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> he that went before <hi>Gregory,</hi> and no leſſe famous in doctrine, and ſanctitie then himſelfe, where he ſaith;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>11.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. cui illata.</note> 
               <hi>Si iniuſta eſt ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, tanto curare eam non debet, quanto apud Deum, &amp; eius ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, neminem grauare debet iniqua ſententia. Ita ergo &amp; ea ſe non abſolui deſideret, qua ſi nullatenus perſpicit obligatum.</hi> Theſe two holy Fathers are not ſo oppoſite as the words may ſeeme to import: But Theologicall doctrine will verie well reconcile this apparent contradiction. There are ſome vniuſt cenſures, becauſe they are denounced with a peruerſe minde and intention; although it were vpon a iuſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe; there is no doubt but all men will yeeld that theſe are to be feared, and that before God they oblige vs, as if they were iuſt: although the Magiſtrate in his wicked inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion offendeth his diuine Maieſtie; and of this it may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that, <hi>ſententia Paſtoris ſiue iuſta, ſiue iniuſta timenda
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17247:38"/> eſt.</hi> Some are in trueth grounded vpon an vniuſt cauſe, though in apparence iuſt, by reaſon that in things hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, the truth is oftentimes ſo concealed, as it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcouer it; ſo that an innocent ſometimes may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned without any fault in the Iudge. This kind of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence obligeth vs not towards God, neither ought it to be feared, before his diuine Maieſtie, or in conſcience, although he condemned be bound to make a ſhew of feare, not to ſcandalize his neighbour, who eſteemeth that ſentence good, and to liue towards God, as his innocencie requireth, before the world, that thinks him culpable (if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the truth) to liue in patience, &amp; ſo to commend his cauſe vnto God: But if the ſentence be vniuſt, denounced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a lawfull cauſe, neither in trueth, nor in apparence, wee muſt not onely not feare it, but with all our power we are bound to oppoſe our ſelues thereunto. This doctrine is eſtabliſhed in eleuen Canons in the Decretorie,<note place="margin">Cáp. qui iuſtus, c. cui illata. cap. ſecundum Catholicam, c. coepisti. cap. remerariè, cap. quod ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe. cap. quò, c. illud planè. c. non debet, <hi>11.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> cap. manet <hi>24.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. ſi quis, <hi>24.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and it is ſo receiued amongſt all Diuines and Canoniſts, that no one of them differs from another; as alſo they agree in this point, that none can be excommunicate, except it be for mortall ſinne, the which muſt be proſecuted alſo, after he hath been firſt admoniſhed by the Church. Hee that will but read all the foreſaid Canons, may be fully inſtructed, that he need no whit to doubt, but that vniuſt cenſures doe no waies ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige or offend, and that they are not to be eſteemed. And ſo much the rather he may vnderſtand this trueth, if he reade but the authors, in the fountaines themſelues, out of whom theſe Canons are taken; for the words both before and after, will make the matter more manifeſt. The ſentence vniuſt in trueth, but yet iuſt in appearance, and which to auoid ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall ought to be feared, cannot grow but from an errour in the fact; for the caſe being deliuered in ſincere trueth, the Iudge which erreth in diſcerning of equitie, though it were through ignorance, is alwaies in fault: therefore whatſoeuer ſentence is vniuſt through manifeſt errour <hi>in iure,</hi> it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor of any validitie, neither doth it binde vs before
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17247:38"/> God, or before the world. In that, for which the Pope thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth out this preſent excommunication, there is no errour at all in the fact, the trueth is moſt cleere, the lawes of the Senate are in writing; the delinquents accuſed and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; there can be no concealed innocencie, which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere to be a fault. The queſtion is, <hi>in iure,</hi> we muſt ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the lawes made, or in the impriſonments decreed, there is any errour committed: for if neither the Prince nor Senate haue offended, but haue contrariwiſe obeyed the commandements of God, in procuring the preſeruation of their ſubiects honours, liues, &amp; goods, as at large in all theſe points hath beene declared; we can no waies doubt of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Senats cauſe, and conſequently of the nullitie of the ſentence Pontificall; but eſpecially and by which this is made manifeſt, there needs not ſuch great dexteritie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to apprehend them, but with very ſlender co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, they appeere manifeſtly to all men: wherefore conſidering the innocencie of the ſame Senate before God, &amp; euidencie alſo thereof before the world, there remaineth no ſcruple, wherein iuſt ſcandall may be giuen. In like maner there is no reaſon why they ſhould in any ſort feare this excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, neither in conſcience, nor in any externall triall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as any one may feare a manifeſt violence offred to a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter end; conſidering it is a manifeſt violence to vſe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of excommunication, granted by Chriſt, contrarie to his owne inſtitutions: and towards him which hath power, and vniuſtly vſeth the ſame, the remedie is to haue recourſe vnto a ſuperior, if he may; but if there be no ſuperior, to whom to haue recourſe, God hath allowed no other remedie to a Prince thus offended, but to make reſiſtance with his owne force, oppoſing himſelfe to force; becauſe it comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, &amp; the ciuil being of euery Common-wealth or kingdome is to the end of his glorie; and therefore a Prince cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit without a ſin and offence, that his owne libertie ſhould be infringed, which is the ciuill being of euerie principallity, and there is no doubt but negligence in defending of it, is a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17247:39"/> greeuous offence vnto God, and moſt hainous, if he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily ſuffer it to be vſurped ouer his head. To obey the commandement of God therefore, wee muſt oppoſe our ſelues againſt him whoſoeuer, that would take away the power which God hath giuen to make lawes, &amp; with iuſtice to defend the foreſaid offended in their liues, honours, and goods. And as the innocent by an error <hi>in facto,</hi> vniuſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, to auoid ſcandall, is bound patiently to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: ſo when the error is <hi>in iure,</hi> and the manifeſt iniuſtice thereof is apparent, to auoid ſcandall likewiſe, the Prince is bound to reſiſt, and to oppoſe himſelfe againſt this iniurie; becauſe there is no doubt, but when this ſhall be knowne to other kingdoms, where the like vnto the Venetian lawes are obſerued, and where malefactors are iudged after a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable maner, that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth for feare of vniuſt cenſures, and thoſe inualidious, hath yeelded vnto violence, and omitted to exerciſe and execute his naturall power, they would be much and exceeding ſcandalized heereat, as alſo the ſubiects that ſhould diſcouer ſuch a vaine feare, they would become very peruerſe. And therefore for this point alſo, it was both equall and neceſſarie for the Prince to make due reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>So that the Popes fulmination being vniuſt and nothing, it followes conſequently, that for neceſſarie defence, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle of the Common-wealth, in the publication and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, hath beene moſt iuſt and lawfull. And the Common-wealths ſubiects, but eſpecially thoſe of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, ought to pacifie their minds and conſciences, attending the ſeruice of God, vnder the protection of the Prince; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly beleeuing, that the holy Ghoſt was promiſed and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to all the faithfull, among whom Chriſt himſelfe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, when they are congregated in his name; and that none can iuſtly be excluded out of the holy Catholicke Church, except by his owne worthy demerits he be firſt excluded from the fauour of God. And that the obedience which God commands vs to performe to our Eccleſiaſticall ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17247:39"/> is not a fooliſh or ridiculous ſubiection; nor the power of Prelates is not an arbitratorie iudgement; but both the one and other muſt be ruled by the Law of God, who in <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> ordeined not an abſolute obedience to the Prieſt, but a preſcribed obſeruance,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> according to the law di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. <hi>Facies quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dixerint qui praeſunt loco, quem elegerit Dominus, &amp; docuerint te iuxta legem eius.</hi> God only is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule, we muſt onely profeſſe obedience vnto him, without all exception. He that generally profeſſeth this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, without the commandements of God, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; and whoſoeuer ſuppoſeth any humane will to be infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, committeth great blaſphemie, in aſcribing to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a propertie onely diuine. Abſolute obedience is onely rendred vnto God, an obſeruance limited within the bounds of lawes diuine. And this they vſed in the ancient Church; we haue an example hereof in the Acts of the Apoſtles, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>S. Luke:</hi> That the faithfull thought the contrarie of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and withſtood him about the vocation of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and yet were they not thundred againſt with hideous excommunications, or threatned by him, and forced to hold their peace; but by the reaſon and authoritie of diuine reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and the words of our Sauiour,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> they were taught and perſwaded. Chriſtian charitie, ſayth <hi>S. Paul, Patiens eſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigna eſt, non inflatur, non eſt ambitioſa;</hi> It threatens not, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes not, it entreateth all men like brothers. Conſidering that Prelates muſt not domineere nor command with em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> but with examples and inſtructions of pietie and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: lets heare <hi>S. Peter</hi> a little; <hi>Paſcite qui in vobis est gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Dei, prouidentes non coacte ſed ſpontaneè ſecundum Deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turpis lucri gratia, ſed voluntariè, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt dominantes in cleris, ſed formafacti gregis ex animo:</hi> and <hi>S. Paul, Non quia dominamur fidei veſtrae, ſed adiutores ſumus gaudij veſtri:</hi> And a Prelats charitie ſhould be as readie to teach, as to be taught of others: for when <hi>S. Peter</hi> erred in <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> forbare not to reprehend him grieuouſly in the preſence of all men: and let no man heere replie, who is like to <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:17247:40"/> that may be ſo bold? as though <hi>S. Paul</hi> by reaſon of his excellencie, might be the bolder to oppoſe himſelfe againſt one, whom it was not lawfull to reſiſt; nay, but we may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and conſtantly affirme quite contrary, who is like <hi>Paul,</hi> that may be compared vnto him in humilitie and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of himſelfe, and of due reuerence to the high Prieſt? Queſtionleſſe we may vndoubtedly beleeue, that as <hi>S. Paul</hi> in all the vertues farre exceeded, whatſoeuer we are able to performe, ſo in due reuerence to the head of the Church,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> he obſerued that, which the leaſt of vs is bound to performe. The holy Scripture ſaith, <hi>Quaecunque ſcripta ſunt, ad noſtram doctrinam ſcripta ſunt.</hi> The holy Ghoſt would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue written this Hiſtorie but for our example, to the end we might imitate it; and we ſee, that all the Doctors in diſcuſſing how any one may oppoſe himſelfe to the Pope, when he commiteth error, and gouernes vnwoorthily, they haue recourſe to this example.</p>
            <p>Let no man therefore be aſtoniſhed, depending onely on the authoritie of a Prelate;<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> let him remember, That not one but two keyes were giuen to <hi>Peter,</hi> and if they be not both vſed together, the effect of looſing and binding doth not enſue; the one being of power, and the other of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and diſcretion. Chriſt gaue not a power to be vſed, without due knowledge and circumſpection, but with great and exquiſite iudgement; the which wanting, power onely takes no effect. The Canoniſts ſay, that the power of binding and looſing is intended by a key, not erring; and <hi>S. Leo</hi> the Pope,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>24.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Manet.</note> expreſly affirmeth it in a Canon, ſpeaking of this priuiledge giuen by <hi>S. Peter: Manet ergo Petri priuilegium vbicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex ipſius fertur aequitate iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, nec nimia est, vel ſeueritas, vel remiſſio, vbi nihil erit ligatum, vel ſolutum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi quod Beatus Petrus ſolue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, aut ligauerit.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17247:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
